They are currently Riverside Excellence Leagues.
They are currently Riverside Excellence Leagues.
Please cancel this session.
Please cancel this session.
Please let Mr. Tong Huni ring旦阛
Please let Mr. Tong Huni ring旦阛
and the ambassador
and the使衿携兄官
receiving the honors of his Korean relationship with the使衿携.
receiving the honors of his Korean relationship with the使衿携.
Hi, I am Wong Huni-J ק่ Easy to ask
Hi, I am Wong Huni-J ק่容易问
Any questions for board members,
Any questions for board members,
this morning I am describing to you
this morning I am describing to you
give this speech
做這個演講
this subject
這個題目
He is also very poetic
他取得也是很有詩意的
epic typhoon
颱風的史詩
in science
於科學尖綜
And the subtitle didn't win on top
然後副標題沒有贏在上頭
The subtitles are in his hand
副標題在他的手上都有
Inaction is something Taiwanese must know
無為台灣人不可不知
Taiwan is
台灣是
OK this is the subtitle
OK 這是副題
Interesting
很有意思
Then I add another subtitle
那我再加一個副題是
Typhoon Night Talk Typhoon Room
颱風夜談颱風室
I hope everyone can go home safely
希望大家能夠平安的回家
before that started
那在開始之前
still take this
還是要把這個
Director Wu introduced to everyone
吳主任介紹給大家
Although there are
雖然上頭也有
but i think
不過我想
we still want this
我們這個還是要
Let me introduce this to you
這個介紹給大家一下
This Professor Wu Junjie
這個吳俊傑教授
it was 1986
是1986年
Graduated from the Department of Atmospheric Sciences of National Taiwan University
畢業於台大的大氣科學系
Then in 1993
然後1993年
Massachusetts Institute of Technology
拿到美國麻省理工學院
Atmosphere of Earth from MIT
就 MIT 的地球大氣
and a Ph.D. from the Department of Planetary Sciences
以及行星科學系的博士
then to this
然後到這個
Princeton University Geophysics
Princeton大學地球物理
Postdoctoral research in fluid power laboratory
流體動力實驗室做博士後研究
After returning to Taiwan
那回來臺灣以後
Worried about doing this research questioned
擔心做這個研究質疑
Research on typhoons
颱風的相關研究
Including the moving strength of the typhoon
包括颱風的移動強度
The Far Wall and the Dynamics of Rainfall
遠牆以及降雨的動力機制
Interaction of Typhoon with Terrain and Ocean
颱風與地形及海洋的交互作用
and make this strategic observation
並且做這個策略性的觀測
It's the wind-chasing project
就是追風計畫
I still came to ask him yesterday
我還有昨天來問他
Their plane flew out again yesterday
他們昨天的飛機又飛出去了
Go to the typhoon show to observe this time
要到颱風演去觀測這一次的
Typhoon Sura and more
蘇拉颱風等等
Research performance is certainly top-notch
研究表現當然是一級棒
2007 2009
2007年 2009年
Awarded twice by Taiwan National Science Council
兩次獲得臺灣國科會的
Lift research award
解除研究獎
It's also the one in 2009
目前也是2009年那個
When the National Science Council was more than 50 years old
國科會50多年的時候
also choose this
也選為這個
One of the 50 scientific achievements of Taiwan
50項台灣的科學成就之一
Currently in the Department of Atmospheric Sciences
現任是大氣科學系的
Distinguished Professor and Head of Department
特聘教授兼系主任
Also serving as the American Meteorological Society's
同時也擔任美國氣象學會的
tropical weather and
熱帶氣象及
member of the hurricane committee
颶風委員會的委員
Also our Republic of China Earth Science Society
也是我們中華民國地球科學學會
published sets
出版的套
editor-in-chief of a scientific journal
這個一個科學雜誌的總編輯
We welcome with warm applause
我們以熱烈的掌聲來歡迎
Director Wu
吳主任
Goodnight everybody
大家晚安
I'm Wu Junjie
我是吳俊傑
I would like to thank Director Peng for the invitation and the introduction just now
要謝謝彭執念長的邀請以及剛剛的介紹
Then I feel very honored to be here today
那我今天覺得非常榮幸能到
Academia Sinica
中研院來
And on this typhoon night
而且在這個颱風夜
see so many
看到這麼多的
Our science community or one of our science popularization circles
我們科學界或者是我們科普界的之一
come with me, let's interact
一同來跟我一起大家來互動
I wish I could today
那希望我今天可以
Shared with you some popular science knowledge and information related to typhoons
跟大家分享了一些科普的跟颱風有關的一些知識跟訊息
can provide us with useful
能給提供大家有用的
very helpful
非常有一些幫助
Then I will briefly introduce this topic to you.
那我簡單就跟大家介紹這個題目可能
The goal given here is a little bit bigger, so I think that when I was concentrating the time in the end
這個給的目標稍微大了一點那我想到最後在做時間的濃縮的時候
I think it will mainly focus on the scientific part
我想主要還是會以科學的部分為主照
that slightly
那稍微
If it is mentioned in the introduction I will put my
如果的介紹有提到我會把我
Some of a book translated a few years ago
過去幾年前翻譯的一本書的一些
Take it out as the subject of today's introductory reading, and then gradually enter the theme of typhoon to be discussed today
拿出來當今天導讀的題材然後逐漸進入今天要談的颱風的主題
OK
OK
That said, I am very touched when the typhoon is coming
那說來也是非常感動在颱風即將到來的這個
This moment of calm before the storm can be gathered here with everyone today
這個暴風雨前的一刻的寧靜可以跟大家今天往上聚在這邊
As Teacher Kun said just now
如同剛剛坤老師所說的
Hope you all come back safe and sound today
希望大家今天滿載而且平安而歸
I think
我想
Not yet maybe but tomorrow night
還沒有到可能不過明天晚上
Let's start with the typhoon that is about to occur.
就從馬上要發生的颱風跟大家講起好了
You may have noticed that we happen to have a typhoon called Sula.
各位可能注意到我們現在剛好有一個颱風就叫蘇啦
Just off the southeast coast of Taiwan
就在我們台灣的東南的外海
already very close
已經非常的近了
It's only about 300 kilometers away from us now.
只現在距離我們只有大概300多公里而已
Then this typhoon is gradually approaching the sea off the northeast corner of Taiwan
那這一個颱風逐漸在往台灣的東北角外海靠近
Then everyone can see that this is actually in the East today.
那各位可以看到這其實今天已經在東
It seems to be doing the weather forecast at seven o'clock now
現在好像在做七點的氣象預報
The typhoon is already very close to the coast of Taiwan
那颱風已經非常靠近台灣的外海
So its airflow also ushers in the rainfall in Huadong area
所以它的氣流也迎來在花東一帶的降雨
Especially between Yilan and Hualien
特別是在宜蘭到花蓮之間
You can see that there has been a lot of rain
各位可以看到已經有比較明顯的降雨
In fact, the rainfall will gradually increase.
那其實這降雨還會逐漸的增大
Then the radar echo may mainly see that the rainband is only the periphery
那這雷達回波可能主要看到這雨帶只是外圍而已
The main rainbands are actually in the south of the typhoon in Taiwan
主要的雨帶事實上都在台灣颱風的南部
Fortunately, these are still in overseas seas
那幸好這些目前都還下在海外海
Then this is its cloud and soil and its position
那這是它的雲土跟它的位置
In fact there is another typhoon at the same time
事實上目前還同時有另外一個颱風
Taiwan is farther away from Japan in this direction
台灣更遠的靠近日本的這個方向
Then the typhoon will continue to move northwestward.
那這個颱風會繼續往西北的方向移動
good
好
What about the typhoon?
那這個颱風呢
In fact, our Central Meteorological Bureau has also made some official forecasts
事實上我們中央氣象局也做了一些官方的預測
You can see that this forecast has also been slightly revised in the past few days.
各位可以看到過去幾天這個預測也有做略微的修正
From the original it was gradually closer to the southern part of Taiwan
從原來是逐漸比較靠近會走向台灣的南部
It became a typhoon to the east of Taiwan two or three days ago
到兩三天前變成到颱風台灣的東部
As of yesterday and today, it has been corrected to the northeast corner or the open sea.
到昨天跟今天已經都修正到東北角落或外海了
Well, although it is impossible for him to cross Taiwan directly
那不過雖然他沒有可能不見得會直接穿過台灣
But if he's around us
不過他在我們附近的話
This threat may still be quite large, especially the rainfall in the east, northeast and north
這個威脅可能還是蠻大的特別是東部東北部跟北部的降雨
In fact, it is possible to be very high
事實上是有可能是會非常的高
So please pay attention
所以還是要請大家留意
In fact, everyone can see that it is Taiwan's prediction that it is actually not read.
那各位事實上可以看到事實上不讀是台灣的預測
In fact, the official meteorological units of countries all over the world have done
事實上全世界各國的官方的氣象單位都有做
Then add that the computer models in each country are predicting
然後再加上各國的電腦模式都在預測
Most of the predictions so far are pretty consistent.
目前大致上多數的預測都還蠻一致的
Pointing to typhoon likely to approach Taiwan's northeast corner
指向颱風可能會靠近台灣的東北角
That's just a prediction of the center of a typhoon
那可是這只是一個颱風的中心位置的預測
But everyone, don't forget that the typhoon itself has a size
可是大家別忘了颱風本身是有一個大小
range of hundreds of kilometers
數百公里的影響範圍的
So in fact, our Taiwan will soon be shrouded in its sphere of influence
所以我們台灣事實上還是很快的就會籠罩在它的影響範圍
So there are some risks, you may want to pay attention
所以是有一些風險的大家可能要留意
Of course, the question that everyone may be most concerned about
那當然大家可能最關心的這個問題
This question is one that I cannot answer
這個問題是我不能回答的問題
Otherwise I'm out of touch
不然我就觸法了
But let me do a simple poll
不過呢我做一個簡單的民意調查好了
If you live in Taipei City, please raise your hand
在座是住在台北市的請舉手
Whoa, please raise your hand in New Taipei City
哇那新北市的請舉手
ok 2 to 1 but almost bigger
ok 2比1不過幾乎大
Please raise your hand in other counties
那其他縣市的請舉手
No, but I'm still very impressed that everyone came
沒有不過我還是很感動大家都來了
However, I think there are two people who can help you answer this question.
不過我覺得有兩個人可以幫忙大家回答這個問題
Then please watch this interview tomorrow
那就請看明天的這個專訪
good
好
what's next
那接下來呢
Let me tell you that we are Taiwan
我就跟大家提就是我們台灣
I just happened to actually go from the US yesterday.
我剛好昨天事實上剛從美國去
Columbia University visit
哥倫比亞大學訪問
and I did a presentation
而且我去做了一個演講報告
I actually found that report very moving.
事實上那個報告我覺得很感動
because of that report
因為那個報告呢
It's about research related to typhoons
講的是跟颱風有關的研究
However, an elderly man in his eighties came
不過來了一個八十幾歲的長者
come and listen to my report
來聽我報告
Then this is called his name is Wallace Broker
那這個叫做他名字叫做Wallace Broker
He's the whole movie after tomorrow
他是就是明天過後這部電影的整個
messenger of scientific theories
科學理論的提出的使者
That is to say why the ocean
也就是在談海洋為什麼
He will have this master of the so-called gentle circulation
他會有所謂的溫妍環流的這個大師
Then when he put forward this hypothesis forty years ago
那他在四十年前提出這個假說的時候
Many people think it is impossible
很多人都認為不可
it's out of the question
這是不可能的
As a result, he is now the researcher
結果現在他就是這個研究的
the most important issue
最重要的一個議題
But very big
不過非常大起
But the main point is
不過主要要講的是
I was on the plane when I got back
我回來的時候在飛機上
Just hear about our nationality airlines
就聽到我們的國籍的航空公司
just playing once
就在播放一聲
This song is promoting the prestige of the country and introducing Taiwan
這首歌就在宣揚國威就是介紹台灣
You may have heard his song
那他那個歌各位或許聽過
just sing whatever
就唱什麼
she famous
Ella Famosa
have you heard
有沒有聽過
In Taiwan, I am fine with him
台灣我他就好
Do you have
有沒有
This is our treasure island
這就是我們的寶島
that was hundreds of years ago
那在數百年前
four or five hundred years ago
四五百年前
When these foreign ships pass by
這些外國人的洋船經過的時候
so call our beautiful island
就這樣稱呼我們這個美麗的島嶼
that's really beautiful
那真的是很漂亮
there are also many poets
也有很多也有詩人
Describe our island in beautiful verse
用美麗的詩句來描述我們這個島嶼
There are mountains, seas, winds and clouds
有山有海有風有雲
That's all introduced here
那都在這裡面介紹了
so very beautiful
所以非常的美
But although we live on this beautiful island
不過雖然我們住在這個美麗的島嶼
But of course it's also nature's creation
不過當然也是這大自然的造化
We happen to be in an area with a lot of environmental hazards
我們剛好在一個環境比較多災害的區域
that is undeniable
那不可諱言的
we who live on this island
我們住在這個島的人
It must also be beneficial for this
也必須對這個要有利
have a certain understanding
有一定的理解
Especially when we face several very large natural disasters
特別是我們面對幾個非常大的自然災害
One is that we all know that the Pacific Rim
一個就是我們都知道這個環澤太平洋區域的
This is the whole volcanic and seismic zone right here.
這是整個火山跟地震帶就在這附近
What about the other side?
那另外一方面呢
is almost the only place where the most active typhoons in the Northwest Pacific must pass.
就是幾乎是西北太平洋最活躍的這些颱風的必經之地
If I list the trajectories of these typhoon layers in this picture
我如果把這些颱風層路過的軌跡都列在這張圖
You can see that Taiwan is at the middle point of its final path.
各位可以看到我們台灣就在它的畢竟的這個路徑的算是中間點
The Philippines, a little to the south, is actually quite serious.
那在南邊一點的菲律賓其實也滿嚴重的
I happened to be eating
我剛好在用餐的時候
Also with a listener who is Mr. Liang
也跟一位聽眾是梁老師
Also mentioned that he said he was also affected by the typhoon
也提到他說他也受到颱風的影響
Affected his itinerary to visit the Philippines
影響到他去訪問菲律賓的行程
Then you can see us in the Philippines
那各位可以看到我們菲律賓
Whether it's the Philippines
不管是菲律賓也好
or Taiwan is here
或台灣就在這個
I'll just call it this aisle called Typhoon
我就把它稱為這個叫颱風的走道上
then i have to be careful
那我不得不小心
We also have to take precautions against typhoons, which can cause disasters.
也不得不防患颱風是會造成災害的
And we have many in Taiwan
而且我們在台灣有很多
There is more rainfall due to the mountains
有更多的因為山引起的降雨
Then the possibility of self-disaster is even greater.
那就自災的可能就更大了
What if we look at some external data?
那如果我們再看一些外面的數據呢
Disaster In fact it is a
災害事實上這是一個
Many This is a World Bank report in 2005
許多這是一個世界銀行在2005年的一個報告
He divides this main disaster atmosphere into six categories
他把這個主要的災害氛圍有六類
For example, including earthquakes and volcanoes
譬如說包括地震火山
This is called landslide
這個叫做土石崩塌
That is, there are still floods, sweat disasters and storms
那個是還有水災 汗災跟風暴
Then among the six major disasters
那這六個主要的災害裡面
What percentage of the population is in each country in the world
全世界的各個國家有百分之多少的人口
under his influence
受到他的影響
Ninety percent of our population in Taiwan
我們台灣有百分之九十的人口
are affected by at least two hazards
是受到至少兩種災害的影響
Seventy-three percent of the population also lives in
百分之七十三的民眾也住在
Areas affected by three hazards
有三種災害影響的區域
So we are paving the way in relatively high-risk areas
所以我們是鋪路在比較高風險的區域
If this picture is used to show
如果用這張圖來顯示
you see our eyes
各位看到我們的眼睛
It is one of the few red zones in the world.
是全世界少數這個最紅的Red Zone裡面
This is an analysis of a company from last year
這是去年的一個公司的分析
It also highlights that
它也凸顯說
There are several economic activities in the world
在全世界有幾個經濟活動
Those who received this very serious extreme disaster
受到這個很嚴重的極端的災害的
Countries exposed to impact
暴露影響的國家
These regions rank fourth in the world
全球第四的就是這幾個地區
except Taiwan
除了台灣之外
The United States, Japan, and mainland China
就是美國、日本還有中國大陸
So we have to guard against typhoons
所以我們不得不防範颱風這個問題
because we're in it
因為我們就身處其中
Then start entering today's regime is a typhoon
那就開始進入今天的政體就是颱風
We are indeed talking about Taiwan
我們的確對台灣來講
On average, we have nearly four typhoons a year
我們平均一年大概有將近四個颱風
will attack us
會侵襲我們
plus although the damage it caused
加上雖然它造成的損失
in fact it is obvious
事實上是很明顯的
This average is just a direct loss
這平均這只是直接的損失
It can probably reach NT$17.4 billion
大概可以達到174億新台幣
In fact, both are more than 0.5
事實上也都超過0.5
3% of nationally produced cats
3%的全國的國民生產的貓兒
on the other hand
而在另一方面呢
We know that disasters caused by typhoons will cause floods
我們知道颱風造成的災害會洪水
In fact, if the typhoon does not come
事實上颱風如果不來
There will be drought in Taiwan
台灣還會有旱災
So it's still very scary for us
所以對我們來講還是非常害怕它
but can't live without it
可是又不能沒有它
That leads us to the question
那這使得我們對這個問題
is to pay great attention
就是要非常的重視
What I will tell you again is that in recent years
我再跟大家報告的就是近年來
Disasters caused by typhoons and floods
颱風洪水的災害
What about some changes that affect us
對我們的影響的一些變化呢
if we start here now
如果我們現在從這裡談起
in 1990
在1990年呢
It was that year, in fact, it was against Taiwan
是那一年事實上是對台灣
The year with the most typhoons
造成最多颱風的影響的一年
A kind of eight typhoons
一種八個颱風
It is the record-breaking typhoon affecting Taiwan
就是破紀錄的颱風影響台灣
Some of them are particularly serious
那其中有幾個特別嚴重的是
is the dean
是院長
it was 2001
是2001年
yes this is 2001
對這是2001年
In 2001 there were two
2001年有兩個
Two of the larger
其中有兩個比較大的
One is Peach Juice and the other is Nali
一個是桃汁 一個是納利
at that time
那個時候呢
since that year
從那一年開始
The entire country of Taiwan has made a more planned disaster prevention and beach prevention measure.
台灣整個國家就做了更有規劃的一個防災的防灘措施
So in later years we can also see
所以在後來有幾年我們也可以看到
Although there are many severe or heavy typhoons passing by
雖然有許多劇烈的或是暴雨的颱風經過
real casualties
真正造成有人傷亡
In particular, the number of deaths has been greatly reduced
特別是死亡的人數大量的減少
So it seems that our active warning at that time
所以似乎我們那時候的主動的預警
These actions related to the so-called evacuation of these dangerous areas
跟這些危險區域的所謂的撤離的這些行動
All have helped to reduce the disaster and casualties
都有幫助減少這個災害跟人員的傷亡
But in 1997
可是到了民國97年
the past 45 years
就是過去45年
The number of people has increased again
這個人數整個又增加回來了
Of course there is a special case because of the Morakot typhoon
當然有一個特例是因為發生了莫拉克的風災
but no matter what
可是無論如何
After analyzing it, the scientists found that
科學家去做了加以分析之後發現
Disasters in recent years are more of the so-called compound type
這幾年的災害更多是屬於所謂的複合型的
It is caused by the combination of elements of many different disasters
它是有很多不同的災害的元素組合起來造成的
It's worth preventing
值得我們要去預防
Its standard procedure is even more rigorous
它這個標準的程序還要再更嚴謹
Or to keep up with the changes in this disaster
或者是要更跟上這一個災害的變化
to cope with it
才能因應它
Let me show you a few examples
那我給大家看幾個例
An example you may be familiar with
各位可能都很熟悉的例子
What about this example of Typhoon Morakot?
那莫拉克的颱風的這個例子呢
means it happened with a very high rainfall
是說它發生了一個非常高的降雨量
Within a limited period of about 3 to 5 days
在有限的大概3到5天的時間之內
What about the super high rainfall?
那這個超高的降雨呢
You can see this from the distribution of rainfall
各位可以看到這從降雨的分布來看
That is to say, it lasts for two or three days.
就是說有長達兩三天的時間呢
Rainfall is very heavy
降雨都非常的大
There are even many times when the rainfall per hour is close to 100 mm
甚至有許多時候每小時的降雨是接近100毫米
That's 10 centimeters, 10 centimeters per hour.
那這個也就是10公分每小時10公分
That went on for hours or more
那連續下了可能數個小時或更多
Well of course it brings it up on the hill for this some
那當然它帶來它在山上的這一些
Our mountain, this oxygen-rich soil
我們的山這個含氧這個土壤
The capacity of oxygen-containing water is already saturated
含氧這一些水的這個能力已經飽和了
So causing that excess pressure on the soil
所以造成那個過大的壓力在土壤
In the end, the whole thing is a landslide or avalanche.
最後整個就是土石滑落或崩塌
This massive avalanche of avalanche
這個大量的崩塌的崩落
Let this unfortunate disaster money
就讓這個很不幸的災錢
This is a still
這算是一個還
It should be a village with a very good environment
應該是一個非常好的環境的村落
Later, Xiaolian Village became like this
後來變成小連村變成這個樣子
that's a big loss
那是重大的損失
It means heavy rainfall
這是說很大很大的降雨
But there is another type of rain
可是還有另外一個類型的降雨
when the typhoon comes
是颱風來的時候
is the total rainfall
是總降雨量不大
But it rained a lot in a short time
可是它在很短的時間下了很多的雨
It rained an average of 600mm in 6 hours
它平均在6個小時之內下了600毫米的雨
About 60 cm of rain
大概60公分的雨
within 6 hours
在下在6個小時之內
Then our general drainage system cannot cope with this kind of
那我們一般排水的系統是沒辦法因應這一種
so-called very rapid heavy rainfall in a short period of time
所謂的非常快速的一個短時的大量降雨
Then this will also cause a flooding event.
那這個也會造成淹水的事件
If this kind of rain falls in Taipei City
那這種雨如果下在台北市的話
No matter how good the water pump in Taipei City is
台北市再怎麼好的抽水機
Maybe it's too late
可能都還來不及因應
so it's a very challenging
所以是一個非常挑戰
that is
也就是
That is to say, we now have some rainfall patterns that are very violent.
就是說我們現在有一些降雨的形態是非常猛烈的
Brings a lot of rain in a short time
在很短的時間帶來大量的降雨
Look at this example also happened two years ago
再看這一個例子也是發生在兩年前
A case you may be familiar with
各位可能也很熟悉的一個個案
typhoon leki
雷基颱風
Please raise your hand if you are impressed
這個有印象的請舉手好嗎
Do you remember if you noticed that
是不是記得如果各位注意到說
At the beginning, the news mentioned the Suhua Highway
當初新聞有提到這個蘇花公路
Unfortunately, two tour buses just fell down
有很不幸的有兩部遊覽車剛好跌
It was this unfortunate accident that washed into the Pacific Ocean.
就是被沖刷到太平洋的這個很不幸的意外
In this example the same means
在這個例子裡面一樣就是說
it's four hours in a very short time
它是在非常短的時間四個小時
More than 100mm of rain falls every hour
每個小時都超過100毫米的降雨
under this amount of rain
在這樣的雨量之下
also caused a lot of collapse
也造成了大量的崩塌
There are some areas like these areas around Suao
有一些像蘇澳一帶的這些區域
The problem of its rainfall causing disasters has been highlighted
它的降雨造成災害的問題就被凸顯出來了
Then this event we are in
那這個事件我們在
Now is the time for the government to regulate the impact of this torrential rain on us
政府現在在管制這個豪雨對我們的影響的時候
It also includes the control of traffic.
還包括對交通的管制都要處理了
Especially on this kind of rough road
特別是在這一種比較險峻的公路上
When the rainfall reaches a certain level
在降雨到達一個程度的時候
its road is closed
它道路要封閉
to avoid this unfortunate situation
來避免這一種不幸的狀況的發生
simply speaking
簡單來講
I put my part about typhoons and disasters today
我把我今天有關颱風跟災害有關的部分
a simple section
一個簡單的小節
report here
在這邊跟大家報告
We probably understand that
我們大概了解就是說
our nature
我們的大自然
Taiwan is in such an environment
我們台灣就處在這樣的環境裡面
Typhoon is a risk of self-disaster
颱風是有很可能自災的風險
These risks are of course mainly related to rainfall
這些風險當然主要跟降雨有關
Of course there are other conditions including address
當然還有其他的包括地址的條件有關
But we also noticed
可是我們也注意到
The larger problem of the whole society
這整個社會更大的問題
includes social change
是包含社會的變遷
population because we have a large population
人口的因為我們人口多
and concentrated
而且又集中
because of land use
在因為土地的利用
Factors such as land development
國土的開發等等的因素
lower limit of stratum etc.
都使了地層下限等
Let this natural original risk factor
都讓這個自然原來的風險的因子
more improvement
更加的提高
what's more
那再加上呢
may be this is a very large one
可能是這是一個非常大的一個
A very important issue in the current scientific community
一個現在科學界的一個很重大的議題
the whole change of climate
就是氣候的整個變遷
That might also bring some new shocks
那也可能帶來一些新的衝擊
This impact includes the global
這個衝擊包括就是全球
What we call the issue of warming
我們所謂暖化的議題
This issue may also cause
這個議題可能也造成
part of the typhoon
部分的颱風
or the torrential rain it brings
或者是它帶來的暴雨
its increased strength
它的強度增強
These changes may make
那這些改變都可能使得
The risks we face are greater
我們所面對的風險更大
In particular, various disasters will also load
特別是各種災害還會負荷
Those neutralizing effects
那這些中和的影響
Let's pave in the higher
就讓我們鋪入在更高的
The environmental risks of these so-called disasters
這些所謂的災害的環境風險裡面
then have to face this problem
那都要去面對這個問題
That's the whole world now
那這也是現在全世界
Not just one that we all pay attention to in Taiwan
不只是我們台灣都在重視的一個
combined with natural science
結合自然科學
Plus socioeconomic and so on
再加上社會經濟等等的
a major issue
一個重大的議題
Then I think everyone today
那我想今天大家
Coming here must also be very concerned about this issue.
來這邊肯定也是對這個議題非常的關心
Well, I just had the chance to meet a few people today.
那我剛剛今天剛好有機會遇到幾個
It happened to be a colleague of the Central Plains Academy
剛好是中原院的同事
The Central Plains Academy also attaches great importance to this issue
像中原院也很重視這個問題
There is also a research center called the Environmental Change Research Center
也有一個研究的中心叫環境變遷研究中心
One of the key issues is also very related to this
其中的一個重點議題也是跟這個很有關
Now the Central Plains Institute is still promoting a
那現在在中原院還在推動一個
with this our worldwide international organization
跟這個我們的世界性的一個國際組織
What about a combined unit?
結合的一個單位呢
It is called IRDR
它就是叫IRDR
It is an internationally relevant one
它就是一個國際相關的一個
a research center related to the so-called method of disaster research
跟所謂的災害研究的方式有關的一個研究中心
there is an office
那有一個office
The office is located in Zhongyuanyuan
辦公室就設在中原院
That's the former Liu Zhaohe and the vice president of our Central Plains Academy
那是我們的中原院的前劉照和副院長
leading this team
正在領導這一個團隊
i think it's a big issue
我想這是一個重大的議題
still in progress
還在不斷的正在進展之中
I think if there is
我覺得在座如果有
Especially young friends who are interested, etc.
特別是有興趣的年輕朋友等等
I think there will be opportunities in the future
我想將來都有機會
Participate in research work related to these
參與相關的這些研究工作
then i'll start now
那我現在就開始進入
typhoon itself
颱風的本身
Then to introduce the typhoon, I will use this picture to start
那要介紹颱風呢我用這張圖開始
In fact if
事實上如果
Of course, few of you here may have the opportunity to say that during a typhoon
當然在座可能很少人有機會說在颱風的時候
I really went inside the typhoon and flew inside to see the typhoon
還真的跑到颱風的裡面用飛機飛到裡面去看颱風
If there is such an experience like this one
如果真的有那樣的經驗就像這一張
in the eye of the typhoon
在颱風的眼裡面
This photo was taken while flying at an altitude of about 3,000 meters
在飛在大概三千公尺的高空所拍的這個照片
What you see is actually very beautiful
所看到的景象事實上是非常的漂亮的
of course we are
我們當然是
say he
說他
From a scientific point of view, he is really a beauty
從科學角度來講他是真的是一個beauty
I say it's a beauty but of course he's also a beast
我說這是美女可是他當然也是一個野獸
that this
那這個
this one
這一個
such a natural
這麼狀觀的一個大自然的
what about him
現象呢他
Topics with lots of interesting science
帶有許多有趣的科學的議題
our nature
我們大自然
Logically speaking
照理說
Why did he produce such a
為什麼他要產生一個這麼
Where's the giant beast monster?
巨大的野獸怪物呢
Why is the normal wind speed ranging from a few meters to 10 meters per second?
為什麼平常風速就是每秒幾公尺到10公尺
Why does it have such an unstable
為什麼它會有這樣的一個不穩定
it will keep increasing
它會不斷的增強
In the end, every year in different corners of some seas around the world
到最後每年在全世界的不同的一些海域的角落
would grow huge so-called storms
就會長出巨大的所謂的風暴
And when it spins, there's no way to stop it
而且當它轉起來的時候是沒辦法停止的
The fastest possible wind speed can be as high as 60-70 meters per second
最快可能風速可以高達每秒60 70公尺
That's basically destroying a lot of
那基本上是可以摧毀非常非常多的
these our trees and more
這些我們的樹木等等
then it's raining
那它下起雨啦
Just like the introduction just now, there are a lot of heavy rain
就像剛剛所介紹的就有很多的暴雨
That's actually a very interesting scientific question
那這事實上是一個非常有趣的科學問題
And when I just ate
而且剛剛吃飯的時候
During the meal, I happened to chat with a colleague
用餐的時候也剛好跟一位同仁聊到
In fact, what about this phenomenon?
事實上這個現象呢
how did it come about
它到底是怎麼產生的
how long can it last
它可以持續多久
how it moves
它怎麼移動
why its strength increases
它的強度為什麼會增強
Then how strong can it be enhanced to the limit?
那它到底能增強到極限有多強
how much rain can it rain
能下多少的雨
Every scientific question is still being explored by many scientists
每一個科學的問題都還在很多科學家的探尋之中
Of course it took many years of hard work
那當然都經過很多年的努力
In fact, we understand more and more about these
事實上我們對這些也有越來越多的理解了
Then of course I will share some interesting parts with you today.
那我當然今天就抽出其中幾個有趣的部分跟大家分享
Another thing to mention is that
那另外要提的就是說
What about the depth of the typhoon?
颱風的深層呢
The most special place is that it can only be found on the sea
最特別的地方是只有在海上才會有
Only in warm enough oceans
在夠溫暖的海洋上才會有
Then it has a very close interaction with the ocean
那它跟海洋有很密切的互動的關係
The interaction with the ocean itself
那這跟海洋的互動本身
Another very interesting natural science question
又是另外一個非常有趣的自然科學的問題
That is, two fluids with different qualities
也就是兩個不同品性的流體
air atmosphere and ocean
空氣大氣跟海洋
a very low density atmosphere
一個密度很低大氣
a dense ocean
一個密度很高海洋
how they go to each other how the wind blows the ocean
他們怎麼去互相風怎麼吹動海洋
How the ocean affects the activity of the atmosphere through the exchange of heat
海洋怎麼透過熱量的交換來影響大氣的活動
that's a very important issue
那這個是一個非常重要的議題
That's inside our typhoon
那在我們颱風裡面
is a very fast atmosphere-ocean interaction
是非常快速的大氣海洋交互作用
Then everyone in this movie after tomorrow
那各位在明天過後的這部電影裡面
What we see is also the interaction of the atmosphere and the ocean.
看到的也是大氣海洋的交互作用
But that effect is a longer-term change
可是那個作用是一個更長時間的變化
One of our oceans may be longer
我們海洋的一個可能是更長
Changes in ocean currents from centuries to millennia
百年到千年的洋流的變化
How to change our climate system
怎麼改變我們的氣候的系統
that's a very fundamental one
那這是一個非常根本的一個
fun big one physical
有趣的大的一個物理的
or natural science issues
或是自然科學的議題
Well, I can’t give you a detailed introduction to the typhoon itself.
那這個沒辦法詳細跟大家介紹台風本身
But I'll drop by and talk to you guys
不過我就順道來跟大家
It shouldn't be called promotion
也應該不叫推銷
should introduce
應該跟大家介紹
This one was just a few years ago
這一本剛好是幾年前
The book that I am involved in translating
我從事參與翻譯的這一本書
This book is called
這一本書呢就叫做
The Vine Wing is talking about the typhoon
The Vine Wing 就是在講台風
That's called a giant wind in America
那在美國叫巨風
the original author of the book
那這本書的原作者
It happens to be my supervisor abroad
剛好是我在國外的指導教授
Then he is a master researcher in this field
那他是一個這個領域的大師級的研究人
the master
的大師
That's also a member of the National Academy of Sciences
那也是美國科學院的院士
That's because my teacher published a book
那因為自己的老師出了一本
It is a very good science book
算是非常好的一個科學的書
I spent a year and a half a few years ago
我在幾年前花了一年半的時間
just translate it into Chinese
就把它翻成了中文
right here
就在這
so come prepared
所以有備而來
If you want to have a deeper understanding of typhoons,
那如果各位想要對台風有更深入的理解的話
in fact the book
事實上這本書
It may also provide you with many useful ideas
也可能可以提供給大家很多有用的思路
Then I will give this book to Mr. Peng first.
那我就先把這本書交給彭老師
Maybe you can pass it on
或許大家可以傳一下
no intention of quitting school
沒有退校的意思
Every library can find it
大家圖書館都找得到
Then what do I think the characteristics of this book are?
那我覺得這本書有什麼特色呢
What about the typhoon it introduced?
它介紹的台風呢
In fact there are scientific issues
事實上有科學的議題
So our topic today starts from this
所以我們今天的題目就從這個
I put the inspiration for translating this book
我當初翻譯這本書的靈感放上去的
it has many scientific issues
它有許多科學的議題
But it is also mixed with a lot of humanities
可是它也夾雜了許多人文
historical and artistic
歷史跟藝術的層面
so i think it's very interesting
所以我覺得它非常有趣
It's worth it when you have time
那值得大家有空的時候
can read
可以翻閱
as if i just mentioned here
就好像我這裡剛剛提到
The topic of our speech today
我們今天的演講題目
it has a typhoon with a historical view
它有歷史觀的颱風
typhoon with scientific dimension
有科學層面的颱風
even literary level
甚至文學層面
I hope this book can give you a
希望這個書可以給大家一個
more complete different aspects
比較完整的不同面向的
this is a scientific question
這一個科學的問題
can i quote today
我今天可以引用呢
In fact, our domestic
就是事實上我們國內
I saw it in today's early starters
我原來有看到今天的初期者裡面
Mr. Zhu, are you here today?
各位朱先生今天有來嗎
Are you in the Humanities or History Institute?
是在人文還是歷史研究所的
Mr. Zhu Malone
朱馬龍先生
Today is good
今天好
i saw his name
我有看到他的名字
in Taiwan University
在我們台大
a few years ago about ten years ago
幾年前大概十年前
I have read a history department
我有讀過一本歷史系的
student research essay
同學的研究說詞論文
Just researching how the typhoon got its name
就在研究說颱風這個名字怎麼來的
did very very detailed
做了非常非常詳細的
analysis of research
研究的分析
In the book I introduced today
在我今天介紹的這本書裡面
He also has a question about how the typhoon came
他也有對颱風怎麼來
There are some analyzes on how the hurricanes in the United States come from
美國的颶風怎麼來都有一些分析
what about in cuba
那在古巴的地方呢
they were in the caribbean a long time ago
他們很早以前在加勒比海
I knew there was such a phenomenon as a hurricane.
就知道有這個颶風的現象的存在
In fact they have some mythical stories
事實上他們還有一些神話的故事
to describe the source of these storms
來描述這些風暴的來源
In fact this of our hurricane
事實上我們這個颶風的這個
What about the word Hurricane?
Hurricane的這個字呢
In fact, it's from these guys over there
事實上就來自在那邊的這一些
including from their Inca culture
包括從他們的印加文化
All the way to the culture of the Caribbean
一直到這個加勒比海的這個文化裡面
there is such wisdom
就有這樣的智慧
to describe this horrible god of evil
來描述這一個恐怖的邪惡之神
Then there is such a stone totem
那還有一個這樣的一個石頭的圖騰
They were all found out later
後來都被找出來
that they think they
那他們是認為他們
This is the storm god they saw
這就是他們所看到的這個風暴之神
It's amazing what people of later generations are thinking about saying
那非常神奇的是後代的人在想說
The typhoon they drew at the beginning rotated
他們當初所畫出來的颱風旋轉的
The direction of the shaft back is already correct.
軸背的方向已經是對的了
Is it a coincidence?
到底是巧合呢
Or are they already available from this one
還是他們已經可以從這一個
The direction of this number of five texts that was blown down
被吹倒的這個數五文的方向拍
But the characteristic that the wind is rotating counterclockwise in the whole northern hemisphere
但出風在整個北半球是逆時針旋轉的這個特性
Then the typhoon symbol in the scientific world of our modern standard is consistent with this, and it is drawn like this
那我們現代的整個標準的這個科學界的台風符號就跟這個一致是這樣被畫出來了
Another very interesting story related to our East is
另外一個跟我們東方有關的一個很有趣的故事是
In fact, these storms are also changing history
事實上這些風暴也在改變歷史
In 1274 AD, it was in Lake Bilie, and at that time the Mongols were considered their kings or emperors
在西元1274年就是在湖畢列也就是那時候蒙古的算是他們的國王或皇帝
After he has unified the entire country of China
他已經統一了整個中國的江山之後
His ambition gradually shifted to wanting to continue to conquer other countries including Japan
他的信誌就逐漸轉移到想要去繼續征服其他的國家包括日本
So in 1274, this Hu Bilie sent his army to combine with the conquered Korea at that time
所以在1274年這個湖畢列就派他手下的大軍結合了那時候已經征服的朝鮮
There is a joint army composed of the Han army, Mongolian army and North Korea
有漢軍、蒙古軍跟朝鮮組成的聯合大軍
an army of one hundred thousand
十萬人的軍隊
At that time, it was already an incredible army
那時候是已經是不得了的大軍
Attack Japan with thousands of these warships
跟數千艘的這個兵艦進攻日本
Then they go directly to the Kyushu area, of course the first line
那他們直接當然第一線就是到九州一帶
What about this ship? It's almost a success.
那這個船呢幾乎就要成功了
They all beat Japan
他們都打贏日本了
The Japanese are losing ground
那日本人都節節敗退
That's because the Mongolian army didn't dare to enter too quickly
那因為蒙古軍也不敢進入的太快
So most of the troops stay on the ship
所以有大部分的軍隊都留在船上
The result is at this time
結果就在這個時候呢
They encountered a miraculous cleansing of a typhoon
他們遇到了一個神奇的一個颱風的清洗
completely annihilated
全軍覆沒
The Japanese put this one
那日本人就把這一個
What about the history of this one?
這一個這一個歷史呢
this one that caused this one
這個造成這一個影響的這一個
become a giant wind
的巨風呢成為是一個
The original meaning of Kamikaze Nahara in Japan is called
神風那原日本的原意是叫
Kamakaze means Kamikaze
Kamakaze就是神風的意思
In 1281, the same history repeated itself
到一二八一年呢同樣的歷史又重演
Later, the original army was attacking Japan
後來原軍在在進攻日本
But in the same situation
可是遇到一模一樣的情況
What about this period of history in Japan?
那這一段歷史呢在日本
There are very detailed records in Japanese books
日本的書上有非常詳細的記載
in 1281
在一二八一年
There is a professor at Merchant Marine University in Tokyo, Japan
日本的東京的商船大學有一位教授
he based on these histories
他就根據這些歷史
with modern technology
用現代的科技
Sheng Na and so on
生納等等
To this open sea of ​​Kyushu
到這一個九州的外海
Yin Island and so on, some Yin Yin Yin Yin
陰島等等的一些陰式陰的陰
the vicinity of these islands
的這些島嶼的附近
To do some biological exploration of the seabed
去做一些海底的一些生納的探測
Including later this unprecedented one
包括後來有這個無人前的一個
vehicle down detection
載具的下去探測
I found many of these
就找到了許多當初這些
At the beginning, this Mongolia or reinforcements
當初這個蒙古或者是援軍
what they left behind
他們所遺留下來的各種
Weapons and some property, etc.
兵器跟一些財產等等
That also indirectly confirms this period of history
那也間接印證了這一段歷史
So this typhoon also changed history
所以這一個颱風也改變了歷史
Without these two or several
如果沒有這兩個或幾個
The impact of the magical typhoon
神奇的颱風的影響
Maybe Japan has changed
那或許日本的已經都被改變了
I don't know what it's like now
那不知道現在又是怎樣的一個
History
的歷史
What about the development?
發展的情形呢
that in this one
那在這一個
this hair
這個發
this of course
這個當然
What about this kamikaze?
這個神風呢
By the time of World War II
到二次世界大戰的時候
This term is of course inspired by Japan
這個名詞當然是被日本拿來激勵
to some extent as
某種程度當成是
a metaphor for them
他們的一個隱喻
as a symbol of their patriotism
來視為他們愛國的象徵
unfortunately
很不幸的就是
organized the so-called kamikaze
組織了所謂神風特攻隊的這個名詞
come from the same noun
是同一個名詞來的
that's unfortunate of course
那當然很不幸的
Many young people were patriotic
許多年輕人當初為了愛國
sacrificed their lives
都犧牲了自己的生命
So the word kamikaze
所以這個神風這個字
Later it was tantamount to being misused
後來是等於是被誤用
or to be quoted
或者是說被引用來
In World War II became
在二次世界大戰成為
symbol of kamikaze
神風特攻隊的象徵
when i was raw
我對原始的時候
Indeed there is such a
的確是有這樣的一個
Nature's arrangement just protects
大自然的安排剛好保護了
Japan at that time
那時候的日本
well here is a brief history
好這是一個簡短的歷史
An introduction to typhoons
跟颱風的一個交解的介紹
Then I introduced it in the nutrition section.
那我在營養段這個書上介紹的
the poem of the poem
這個詩的詩
Of course three to four to one
那當然三四比一
He may not have personally met the so-called Hurricane
他或許本人沒有親自見過所謂的Hurricane
when i dined like today
我今天一樣用餐的時候
Teacher Liang, a colleague asked me
梁老師有一位同仁問我說
Why there are no typhoons in Europe
為什麼歐洲沒有颱風
Then of course I can add more to you later.
那我當然後面也可以跟大家再補充
Basically the only place where a typhoon has a chance to form
基本上颱風他唯一有機會形成的地方
in the warmer waters of the tropics
是在熱帶比較溫暖的海域
So whether in the Atlantic or the Pacific
所以不管在大西洋或太平洋
After these hurricanes formed
這些颶風形成之後
Just in these tropical regions are in the so-called envelope belt
剛好在這些熱帶區域都在所謂的信封帶
Take him in Dongfeng and move west
在東封帶他就往西移動
So he has no chance to go north
所以他就沒有機會往北
Or go northeast to Europe
或往東北到歐洲去了
So there is no typhoon in Europe
所以歐洲是沒有颱風的
So Shakespeare itself certainly didn't
所以沙士比亞本身肯定是沒有
Experienced a real Hurricane
經歷過真正的Hurricane
But in this UK or off the coast of Europe
可是在這一個英國或是歐洲的外海
It could also be that there are a lot of storms
也可能是有非常多的風暴
these may be winter storms
這些可能是冬天的風暴
not a summer storm
不是夏天的風暴
the more different its physical properties
它物理的品性越有不同
Written in these famous classics of their history
寫在他們歷史這些著名的經典裡面
They also take this so-called power of nature
也都把這個大自然的這個所謂的威力
This horrific situation with this torrential rain force
跟這個豪雨勢力的這個恐怖的情境
described very very vividly
描述的非常的非常的生動
If you are interested, you can read the Chinese and English parts separately.
如果各位有興趣可以分別對這些中英文的部分
Or the Chinese part we translated
或者是我們翻譯的這個中文的部分
trying to experience
在加以體驗
Then today I will probably do a very simple one.
那今天大概是做一個很簡單的一個
an introduction
一個介紹
what about this end of america
那在美國的這一端呢
That's another famous poet I also visited
那這是另外一位著名的詩人我也去拜訪過
he commemorates him
他的紀念他
The place where he was born because he is in Ma Chau
誕生的地方因為他就在馬洲
Then this one Emily Dickinson wrote this song
那這一個Emily Dickinson他寫的這一首
This poem is also very beautiful and talks about the wind and rain
這一首詩也非常的美也談到了這個風還有雨
water etc.
水等等
I just happen to
那我剛好
After this translation, I cooperated with one of my juniors last year and now it has become a song
這個翻譯之後呢我去年跟我的一位學妹合作現在已經變成一首歌了
Maybe those who are interested, I can broadcast it to everyone in the future
那或許有興趣的同仁我以後可以播給大家
Ok, let's go back to Typhoon
好那我們再回到颱風
We are influencing what is going to happen in our Taiwan today
我們今天正在影響我們台灣即將要發生的這個
What about the Sura typhoon we just talked about?
我們剛剛講的這個蘇拉颱風呢
Some newspapers you may have heard say
有一些報紙可能各位已經聽到說
Everyone is worrying about it's so-called dot
大家在擔心它是所謂的點
Possibly a Northwest station
有可能是一個西北台
If you notice the news
各位如果注意到新聞的話
You may have heard the term
可能有聽到這個名詞了
Let me explain to you what Northwest TV is doing.
就跟大家解釋一下什麼是西北台做開端
In 1996, there was a typhoon cleaning Taiwan called Hebo Typhoon
在1996年的時候有這一個颱風清洗台灣叫賀博颱風
If anyone here has any impression, please raise your hand
在座還有沒有人有印象的請舉手一下
Not bad, it seems that everyone is also deeply affected by it
還不錯好像大家也是有深受其影響
This typhoon landed in Keelung from the northern part of Taiwan and then left Taiwan.
這個颱風呢就從台灣的北部經過基隆一帶登陸然後離開台灣
But what?
不過呢
It was the strongest typhoon in those years
它是那幾年裡面最強最強的一個颱風
that's what we're doing
那我們為了這個就是我們在
On the Taipei Line, there is another mine stall on the top of Wufen Mountain in New Taipei City.
在台北線又是新北市有一座五分山的山頂上設的一個雷檔
The original scene
當初所拍到的情境
This radar is very telling
這個雷達非常有故事性
because the whole radar
因為整個雷達
The so-called modern radar
所謂這個現代化的雷達
Setup in Taiwan
在台灣的設置
this is the first
這是第一顆
is the highest technology
就是最高科技的
The modern one is called Duppler's
現代化的叫杜普勒的
new radar
新的雷達
it can detect
它可以偵測到
distribution of rainfall
降雨的分布
and typhoon wind
以及颱風的風的
indirect estimate
間接估計
Doppler effect
用杜普勒效應
wind speed can be estimated
可以估計風的速度
This radar in 1996's
這個雷達在1996年的
Set on July 23
7月23號設好
original design
當初的設計
It can tolerate winds of 65 meters per second
它可以容忍每秒65公尺的風
it is well designed
它設計好
only a week
才一個禮拜
July 30-31, 1996
1996年7月30到31號
Typhoon Herb directly
赫伯颱風就直接
center passes nearby
中心在附近穿過去
The result is very accurate
結果非常精確
This typhoon is as high as every second
這個颱風高達每秒
70 meters
70幾公尺
very precise
非常精確的
This radar is destroyed
這個雷達就被摧毀了
this is also
這也是
karma
因緣際會
Our Nature Benefits
我們的大自然好處
like know what we're doing detection
像知道我們在做什麼偵測
Of course it took another year to rebuild
那當然後來又花了一年重建
well that's an interesting story
好這是一個很有趣的故事
But the point of this typhoon is that this typhoon passes by like this
不過這個颱風呢重點是這個颱風這樣經過呢
The wind of the typhoon revolves counterclockwise
颱風的風呢是逆時針在環繞
So in Taiwan when he was close to Taiwan and still here
所以在台灣他靠近台灣還在這裡的時候
The place where Taiwan's fresh water exits is blowing
台灣這淡水的出口的這個地方呢是吹
probably northerly to northwesterly
大概北風到西北風
So he will block the flooding of our freshwater river
所以他會阻擋這個我們的淡水河的排洪
The Danshui River is collected from the Xindian Creek Keelung River
那淡水河呢是收集從新電溪基隆河
The only exit with the Great Khan Creek
跟大汗溪整個的唯一的出口
So his whole water is accumulated
所以他整個水就是累積起來
and then add the metropolitan area rainfall
然後加上都會地區降雨
so the whole place is flooded
所以整個地方都淹水
so in taipei
所以在台北
For example, the setting island in Taipei City, etc.
比如說台北市的設置島等等
Both sides of this West River are completely flooded
這個西一水的兩岸全部都淹
very severe flooding
非常嚴重的淹水
Then this situation becomes Northwest TV
那這種情況就成為西北台
So Northwest TV should refer to
那所以西北台應該所指的是
Only typhoons pass by here to bring this water
只颱風從這裡經過帶來這個添水
When the northwest wind blows in the northwest corner of Taiwan
在台灣的西北角會吹西北風的時候
this typhoon
這種颱風
Then this kind of typhoon will easily cause relatively severe disasters in our Taipei county and city
那這種颱風在我們台北縣市就會容易造成比較劇烈的災害
Our typhoon this time is coming from here
我們這一次的颱風是比較偏從這邊上來
But it may slowly turn around like this
可是它有可能慢慢會這樣轉過來
So have features like
所以有類似的特徵
So we need to be more cautious in our northern places
所以在我們北部的地方的確是需要比較謹慎小心
Well, this is called Xibeitan
好這叫西北潭
then i won't repeat it
那我就再不再重複了
I will introduce a few terms to you today
我今天給大家介紹幾個名詞
Another one that everyone still remembers is Typhoon Nali 10 years ago in 2001
那另外有一個各位記憶猶新的是10年前的納利颱風 2001年
What is special about this typhoon is
那這個颱風的特別的地方是
it's already in september
它已經在9月份了
At this time, the sea temperature is already relatively low.
這個時候事實上海溫已經比較低了
It stands to reason that typhoons are less likely to stay in the same place for too long
照理說颱風比較不容易在同一個地方存留太久
But it brushed down from the northeast with a very peculiar trajectory
不過它以非常奇特的軌跡從東北這樣刷下來
Took 49 hours to pass through Taiwan
花了49個小時通過台灣
very slow
非常緩慢
that would cause a lot of accumulated rainfall
那就造成大量的累積的降雨
because it moved for a long time
因為它移動了非常久
raining
雨一直下
It rains all the time, but the ocean continuously provides water vapor for the typhoon to turn into rainfall
雨一直下可是海洋不斷的提供水蒸氣給颱風變成降雨
So we have a lot of rain here, especially in the metropolitan Taipei area
所以我們這邊下了非常多的雨特別是都會的台北區域
You all know that it caused a serious incident at that time.
那各位也知道那時候造成了比較嚴重的
Situation of stagnant water
積水的情況
Let me tell you about another type of typhoon called Morakot.
我再給大家講的是另外有一個類型的颱風這叫莫拉克颱風
this typhoon
這個颱風
happened three years ago
是在三年前發生的
He himself caused the so-called baba flood
他本身造成了所謂的巴巴水災
His wind is not very strong
他的風不是很強
He's just a basic moderate typhoon
他只是一個最基本的中度颱風而已
But he moved very slowly before he passed Taiwan
可是他在通過台灣之前他移動的非常的慢
plus
加上呢
what about this season
這個季節呢
He is in early August, July to August
他這是一個8月初7到8月的時候
We happen to be in the whole of Asia
我們剛好處於整個亞洲
When the southwest monsoon prevails and intensifies
西南的季風在盛行在加強的時候
What about this strong monsoon?
那這個很強的季風呢會把
This place in the South China Sea is very humid and warm air brings up
在這個南海的地方很潮濕暖的空氣帶上來
Although the typhoon is
雖然颱風是在
On the east side of Taiwan, the warm and humid air brought up by the southwest airflow
在台灣的東側 可是西南的氣流帶上來的暖溼空氣
Will be affected by typhoon and terrain
會受到颱風跟地形的影響
will cause a lot of rain in the southwestern part of Taiwan
會在台灣的西南部造成大量的降雨
When this pattern and this form appear
這個pattern 這個形態出現的時候
In the southwest but not in the center of the typhoon
在西南部反而不在颱風的中心
while in the southwestern plains and mountainous areas there is a lot of rainfall
而在西南部的平地跟山區有大量的降雨
That caused a very serious so-called bus storm disaster
那就造成了非常嚴重的所謂的大巴風災
Morakot's Storm has another feature
莫拉克的風災還有一個特性
It's the role of the southwest airflow that I just mentioned.
就是我剛剛提的就是西南氣流的角色
From now on, we now understand everyone's understanding of the entire typhoon prevention
我們現在從此大家對整個颱風的防範的理解
it's a little more complicated
是還要再更複雜一點
In addition to considering the changes in the wind and rain of the typhoon itself
除了要考量颱風本身風雨的變化之外
Also consider our larger scope
還要考慮我們更大範圍
The role of the incoming southwesterly gusts over hundreds of kilometers
幾百公里範圍外所帶進來的西南激風氣流的角色
When the airflow is strong
那這個氣流當它很旺盛的時候
is possible
是有可能的
may have additional effects
可能造成額外的影響
Of course, the impact will be more serious in the southwestern part of Taiwan.
那這個影響當然是在台灣的西南部是會更嚴重
Another thing to mention here is that
那這裡另外要提的是
What about this particular case of our Morakot?
這個在我們莫拉克的這一個特殊的個案裡面呢
let's take a look
我們來看一下
This is the storage capacity of two reservoirs in southwestern Taiwan
這是台灣西南部的兩個水庫的蓄水量
They are Wushantou Reservoir and Zhenwen Reservoir respectively.
分別是烏山頭跟真文兩個水庫
The two reservoirs were counted from January 2009
這兩個水庫在2009從1月開始算
Everyone sees that the water is getting less and less
各位看到水越來越少
Because there was very little rain in the whole spring that year.
因為那一年整個春雨非常的少
So getting dry is its benefit
所以越來越乾那是它的乾濟
By June and July of that year, the water volume had reached
到那一年的六七月的時候水量已經到
Compared with the so-called water shortage situation
比較所謂的缺水的情境了
But a typhoon came on August 8
不過呢單一八月八號的一個颱風來臨
dramatic increase in water
水劇烈的增加
Just because of the cleaning of Typhoon Morakot
就因為有莫拉克颱風的清洗
Then what
然後呢
excess water
超水量
But what about after the water caused the flood?
可是這些水造成水災之後呢
It quickly lost to the sea again
它很快的又流失到海裡面去
So the reservoir can't hold so much water
所以水庫也流不下這麼多的水
So then suddenly the drought came next door
所以然後又突見乾旱到隔壁
Every other year until another new typhoon comes
隔年一直到又有新的颱風來的時候
There is water in the reservoir
水庫才又有水
So the arrangement of our reservoir in Taiwan
所以我們台灣的水庫的安排
In fact, it has a lot to do with how to grasp the dynamics of the typhoon
事實上跟怎麼掌握颱風的動態也很有關係
The reservoir wants to keep the water a little more
水庫又想把水裝保一點
But I'm afraid it will burst again
可是又怕一次塞爆了
If it drains water when the typhoon is strongest
它如果在颱風最強的時候要排水的話
The disaster will be more serious
災害又會更嚴重
So this is a very big learning
所以這是一個非常大的學問
This is why we in Taiwan are suffering from this drought
這也是為什麼我們台灣在這個旱災
Alternate process of water shortage or flood
比較有缺水或者是水災的交替過程
Part of the reason it's very difficult
非常處境非常艱難的部分原因
I just mentioned that typhoon Morakot will cause such a large amount of precipitation
我剛剛提到會造成莫拉克颱風這麼大量的降水
partly caused by accumulated precipitation
部分的原因累積的降水
because it moves very slowly as it passes
是因為它通過的時候移動得非常慢
In a slow process, it can continue to rain
慢的過程它就可以不斷的下雨
It's been a long time
下了比較久
This process is also closely related to the topography of Taiwan.
這個過程跟台灣的地形也息息相關
Main file of Taiwan terrain
台灣地形的主檔
You can imagine our terrain itself
各位可以想像我們的這個地形本身
about three kilometers high
大概有三公里高
There are even places close to four kilometers
甚至有地方接近四公里
Under the main file of this high mountain in Taiwan
在台灣的這個高山的主檔之下
Although the development of the vertical airflow of the typhoon itself
雖然颱風的本身的垂直氣流的發展
range of rotation possible
旋轉的範圍可能
up to a height of ten kilometers
可以高達十幾公里的高度
But its strongest part is within a few kilometers of the lower floors
可是它最強的部分就是在低層的幾公里範圍
I just received a word from Shan’s main file at this place
在這個地方剛好收到山的主檔的話
the airflow will change
氣流就會改變
Then we can't flow to
那我們因為氣流不能流到
land inside
陸地裡面去
it will be blocked
它會被擋住
Then we can see that the terrain is actually changing the state of the typhoon's movement
那我們就可以看到地形事實上在改變颱風的運動的狀態
So if we want to make more accurate typhoon predictions
所以如果我們要對颱風的預測要更精確的話
It may be necessary to have a better understanding of how terrain affects typhoons
可能要對地形怎麼影響颱風也要有更好的理解
This is also one of the reasons why it is more difficult for us to predict typhoons
這也使得我們對颱風的預測更困難的原因之一
What about the last example?
最後一個例子呢
just mentioned
就是剛剛提到
Many people have raised their hands to affect this in an event in Shuo
許多人都舉手影響到樹奧的一個事件的這個
Meiji Typhoon
眉積颱風
You may also know when this typhoon occurs
各位可能也知道這一個颱風發生的時候
it's raining a lot here
這裡下了非常多雨
Especially in the Shuao area
特別是孰傲一帶
But where is the typhoon?
可是這樣颱風在哪裡呢
Do you have any impression
各位有沒有印象
where was the typhoon at that time
颱風那個時候在哪裡
When Typhoon Maegi occurred
在梅姬颱風發生的時候
Typhoon Meiji is not in Taiwan at all
梅姬颱風根本不在台灣
He is over the South China Sea
他在南海上空
he passed the philippines
他通過菲律賓
He is so far away
他好遠哦
we call it a
我們稱這是一個
Typical effect called Qiutai
典型的叫秋台的效應
Everyone, if we see you again this fall
各位如果今年秋天再看到
When a typhoon approaches us
有颱風靠近我們的時候
Notice if the term is mentioned
注意到會不會有提到這個名詞
in autumn
在秋天的時候呢
Typhoons sometimes go very low
颱風有時候走得非常低
in the South China Sea
在南海上
You can see that they are all in this area
各位可以看到都在這一帶
are near the South China Sea
都在靠近南海的地方
But Taiwan is raining
可是台灣卻在降雨
how so
怎麼會這樣
then there is one
那這是有一個
I'm on this topic
我在這個議題上
There are also some research results
也有做出一些研究的成果
Then I made a schematic diagram like this
那我做了一個這樣的一個示意圖
typhoon though
颱風雖然
In the South China Sea, but its airflow is like this
在南海上,可是它的氣流是這樣繞的
It just started with autumn and the low atmosphere
剛好跟秋天開始低沉的大氣
The atmosphere below about 1500 meters has the northeast monsoon
大概1500公尺以下的大氣有東北季風
start to strengthen
開始在加強
because we know autumn is coming
因為我們知道秋天來了
Gradually the northeast monsoon
逐漸的就有東北季風
Then their two winds will meet here
那他們這兩股風會在這裡匯流
will be on the east side of Taiwan to the northeast corner
就會在台灣的東側到東北角
form this conforming airflow
形成這個符合的氣流
Then the corresponding airflow will rise if it is blocked by the mountain
那這個符合的氣流又被山擋住就會上升
that would result in the so-called
那就會造成所謂的
easy to produce more rainfall
容易製造更多的降雨
So the rain falls on the east side of Taiwan
所以降雨都在台灣的東側
What about this effect?
那這一個效應呢
Some people call it the co-hosting effect
有人稱它叫共辦效應
refers to the swirling airflow of a typhoon
指的就是颱風的旋轉的氣流
with northeast monsoon
跟東北季風
an effect of co-existence
共同相伴造成的一個作用
Then this effect happens in autumn
那這個作用都發生在秋天
So what we call the Qiutai effect
所以我們稱為秋台的效應
There are often typhoons far away from us in autumn
那在秋天時常有離我們很遠的颱風
caused major disasters in Taiwan
就造成台灣的重大的災情
Just like the typhoon over there
就像剛剛那邊機台風
Then I spent 30 minutes briefly introducing many basic characteristics of typhoons to everyone.
那我簡單跟大家很快的花了30幾分鐘時間介紹了颱風的許多基本的特徵之後呢
Then in the last paragraph of the first stage today, I will tell you that the problem of typhoon is not just the typhoon itself.
那我今天的第一階段的最後一段就跟大家提另外其實颱風的問題不是只有颱風本身而已
Now a topic that many people in the scientific community are concerned about is that if our climate changes
現在很多科學界全世界大家都在關心的一個議題就是如果我們的氣候變化了
Will our typhoon-like storms change accordingly?
那我們像颱風的這一種風暴會不會跟著改變
How is typhoon related to climate?
那颱風跟氣候怎麼連結呢
Then I will use a few simple slides to report some progress in this regard
那我用幾個簡單的投影片跟大家報告這方面的一些進展
Then this is a picture that you may be more familiar with.
那這一張是可能各位比較熟悉的一個圖片
It's too much to talk about is that this is all the temperature observations we have all over the world
這太談的就是這是我們全世界所有的溫度的觀測
An average of observations of the Earth's surface temperature
地表的溫度的觀測的一個平均值
We see that from the last century all the way to our past
我們看到從在上個世紀一直到我們過去
temperature over the past few years
去幾年的溫度
Characteristics of changes in global mean surface temperature
全球的地表平均溫度的變化的特徵
Then we obviously see
那我們當然很明顯的看到
It's a well-known feature
這是一個大家都知道的特徵
is talking about
就是在談的就是
The phenomenon of global warming that we have experienced in the last hundred years
我們在近百年的全球暖化的現象
to the past hundred years or so
到過去一百年左右呢
Our global surface temperature has increased
我們全球的地表溫度增加了
about 0.74 degrees
大約是0.74度
that doesn't seem like much
那看起來好像不多嘛
because we go from morning to night
因為我們每天的早上到晚上
In winter, the weather changes by more than ten degrees.
在冬天的天氣變化就有十幾度了
So why should we worry about this 0.74 degree?
那我們為什麼要擔心這個0.74度呢
Because this 0.74 is a global average
因為這0.74是一個全球的平均值
You want the global average to be
你要讓全球的平均同時要
To increase there is a systematic increase so much
要增加有系統的增加這麼多
Indicates that our climate is changing
表示我們氣候是在做改變的
Then this is not a completely negligible data
那這不是一個完全可以忽略的數據
Then this obvious change
那這一個明顯的變化
That's what everyone cares about right now
就是大家目前非常關心的
global warming issue
全球暖化的議題
So what are the reasons for this phenomenon?
那至於有哪些原因造成這個現象
That might be another speech to talk about
那可能是另外一個演講可以談的
For example, the birth effect, the human-induced birth effect, etc.
譬如說 問世效應 人為引起的問世效應等等
So what we're going to talk about today is
那我們今天要談的是
under such a condition
在這樣的一個條件之下
Scientists or scholars who we are very concerned about social economy will come out
科學家或者是我們非常關心社會經濟的學者要問世
Our Future Affects Our Rainfall
我們未來會影響我們的降雨
and storm system
還有風暴系統
Will there be systemic changes as well?
會不會也跟著有系統性的改變
He will also be characteristically different
他也會有特徵性的不一樣
then to understand the problem
那要了解這個問題
especially the typhoon
特別是颱風的問題
We're going to start with the most basic research
我們要從最基本的研究著手
This research is very basic
這一個研究倒是非常基本的
show us some clues
給我們看出一些眉目
what eyebrows
什麼眉目呢
This is a very well-known research scholar
這分別是一個非常知名的研究學者
When he puts the world's typhoons at their strongest
他把全世界颱風達到最強強度的時候
how strong is he
他的那個強度有多少
Compared with the sea temperature conditions at that time
跟那個時候所在的海溫條件
as a study of every point
作為一個每一點的研究
Under certain conditions, there is a typhoon whose intensity reaches 40 meters, etc.
在某個條件之下,有一個颱風,他的強度達到40公尺等
He just clicked out every point, so many points
他就把每一個點都點出來,點了這麼多點
There are the North Atlantic Ocean and the Northeast Pacific Ocean respectively, which are near the coast of Mexico
分別有北大西洋、東北的太平洋,這是靠近墨西哥外海
And the Pacific Ocean in the Northwest is near us
還有西北的太平洋就是我們附近
All points find a common feature
所有的點都找到一個共同的特徵
This common feature is that we found that if the sea temperature is higher,
這個共同的特徵就是我們發現海溫如果越高的話
The lowest distribution of typhoon is still so low, but the maximum value of the strongest and strongest part is getting bigger and bigger
颱風的分布最低還是這麼低,可是最強最強的部分最大值越來越大
In other words, roughly one of the properties of an observation that appears to be
換句話說,大致顯示的一個觀測的特質就是
As long as the sea temperature is relatively high, the range where the typhoon may reach the strongest intensity will be relatively strong
只要海溫比較高的話,颱風可能可以達到最強的那個強度的範圍都會比較強
Just like the cover given by this red line
就好像這個紅線給的蓋子一樣
Vertices are getting bigger and bigger
頂點是越來越大
But what about individual typhoons?
可是個別的颱風呢
big and small
有大有小
incomparably larger
無間的比較大
But its strongest is bigger
可是它的最強比較大
so its average
所以它的平均值呢
will go up a bit
也會列往上升一點
Average typhoon from here to here
這裡到這裡的平均的颱風
about this strong
大概這麼強
But the average from here to here
可是這裡到這裡的平均值
Average values ​​at this sea temperature are here
在這個海溫下平均值在這裡
So basically it's telling us
所以大致上都在告訴我們
when we have global warming
當我們如果有全球暖化的時候
higher sea temperature
比較高的海溫
may offer more favorable conditions
可能提供比較有利的條件
Give the typhoon a chance to be stronger
讓颱風有機會更強
But of course there are a few typhoons
可是當然也有少數颱風
For different reasons the comparison is not very strong
因為不同的原因比較沒有很強
that's possible
那是可能的
But its statistical average properties
可是它的統計的平均特性
will be stronger
會比較強
What about this feature?
那這一個特性呢
a few years ago
在幾年前呢
There is a very well-known research unit
有一個非常知名的研究單位
That
那
I just happened to serve in this research unit in the past
我過去剛好在這一個研究單位服務
called Princeton University
叫Princeton大學的
geodynamics
叫做地球動力
Fluid Power Laboratory
流體動力實驗室
they use computers
他們就用電腦
to simulate this feature
去模擬出這個特徵
This characteristic is to say
這個特徵是說
in a modern climate
在現代的氣候下
The distribution of typhoon intensity is roughly like this
颱風的強度的分布大概是這樣
Then here is the central air pressure of the typhoon
那這下面是颱風的中心氣壓
That is the number of typhoon occurrences
那這是颱風的各發生的各數
In other words
換句話說呢
If the line moves west and left,
如果這個線越往西左邊移的話
The lower the central air pressure, the stronger the typhoon
中心氣壓越低就表示颱風越強
So here is the frequency distribution plot of the past distribution
那這是過去分布的頻率分布圖
So this is the later, rougher time limit?
那這是後的這個比較粗的時限呢
is talking
是在講
100 years later
100年後
If our planet's carbon dioxide doubled
如果我們地球的二氧化碳增為兩倍
After that doubled
那增為兩倍之後
Global temperatures could increase by a few degrees C after
全球溫度可能會增加幾度C之後
new climate line
新的氣候條線下
The typhoon that their computer sees
他們電腦所看到的颱風的
The distribution of the activities of the situation
的分布的活動的情況
Then the entire line moves to the left on average.
那這整個線平均都往左邊移了
That means it does change in average strength
那代表它的確平均的強度在改變
more obvious
比較明顯
So what was asked above
那所以上面問的
As for this question, their answer is yes, it will be stronger
這個問題呢,他們的答案是沒錯是會更強
But I added a butt
不過我加了一個butt
We also see that this total area represents the total number of typhoons
我們也看到這個總面積代表是颱風的總個數
but slightly reduced
卻稍微減少了
In other words, we have more strong typhoons around the world
也就是說我們全世界有更多的強的颱風
But the total number of typhoons has decreased
可是總颱風數變少了
In other words
換句話說呢
Smaller and weaker typhoons are also less and more
比較小比較弱的颱風也變少了更多
That is to say, the whole world concentrates the main energy in a specific relatively strong typhoon.
也就是全球把主要的能量都集中在特定的比較強的颱風裡面
Such changes can indeed have an impact on our lives and our environment
這樣的變化對於我們的生活跟我們的環境的確是可以有衝擊的
This feature is our climate system
這個特徵就是我們的氣候系統
After warming, it is possible to create more strong typhoons
在暖化之後是有可能製造更多很強的颱風
Then this one is the result of a single study
那這一個是單一的研究結果
currently published
目前發表的
However, in recent years there have been more new results
不過近年有更多新的結果
Both reflect similar consistent features
都反映類似一致的特徵
This feature refers to the
這個特徵就是在提到說
The future is actually not just typhoons
未來事實上不只是颱風
under the new climate
在新的氣候形態之下
warmer
比較暖的
Under this global warming climate pattern
這個全球暖化的氣候形態之下
Our storms may also be stronger
我們的暴雨也可能會更強
but at the same time
可是同一個時候
drought in places where water is scarce
那些本來缺水的地方的乾旱
That is, our climate is extreme.
也就是我們氣候極端化了
Then this is the result of what we call polarization
那這一個我們說兩極化的結果
Of course it belongs to
當然是屬於
Make our climate important to our survival
讓我們的氣候對於我們的生存
In fact there are larger
事實上是有更大的一些
Threats and challenges exist
威脅跟挑戰存在
So far this issue
那這個議題到目前
still under study
還在研究之中
is what we are currently engaged in
是我們目前從事相關的
A Hot Topic in Atmospheric Research
大氣研究的一個熱門的議題
what i just said
那我剛剛講的是
slightly simpler
稍微比較簡單一點
In fact, there are many details
事實上裡面有很多的細節
there are still some uncertainties
還有一些不確定性
There are also some scientists who have many
也有一些科學家有不少
Different theories and different views
不同的理論跟不同的看法
Then these have to be clarified with updated research.
那這些都有帶更新的研究要去釐清
But I think the concept I'm talking about so far is roughly
不過我想我目前談的這個概念大致是
It's acceptable, you can take him
可以接受各位可以把他
take home
帶回家的
what about this question
那這個問題呢
A few years ago the World Meteorological Organization of the United Nations convened many scientists
在幾年前聯合國的世界氣象組織召集了許多科學家
meeting together
一起開會
Then I happened to participate in this conference, which was quite interesting at the end of 2006.
那我剛好有參與了這個會議這個會議也蠻有趣的2006年的年底呢
Meeting in Costa Rica, singing poems and leaving home
在Costa Rica開會歌詩大離家
That
那
then i will go to this country for a meeting
那我去這個國家開會
The happiest and most gratifying thing
最開心最欣慰的一件事呢
The first visa-free because it is a country with diplomatic relations with us
第一個免簽證因為是我們邦交國
The second is the holiday between us to visit his national park is the National Park of the Living Mountain
第二呢是我們中間的假日呢就去參觀他的國家公園是活活山的國家公園
You may not believe it
各位可能不不敢相信
There are only two flags in the entire national park
整個國家公園只有兩種旗幟
One is the national flag of Geshi Dalijia and Dalijia
一個是歌詩大離家的大離家的國旗一個呢
The national flag of the Republic of China is all over the mountain
中華民國的國旗滿山
why
為什麼呢
Because that national park belongs to Renyang of the Republic of China
因為那個國家公園是我們中華民國任陽的
But it's a very, very positive thing
可是這是非常非常正面的一件事
So it's also gratifying
所以也令人欣慰
but
不過
What I want to apologize to everyone is that we broke up the next year.
我要跟大家道歉的是隔年就斷交了
so
這樣
I haven't been back yet
我還沒有再回去過
but anyway
不過無論如何呢
what about this meeting
這一個會議呢
Basically, I made a few conclusions, saying that this issue is very, very important.
基本上就做了幾個決論就是說這個問題非常非常重要
but there are some
可是還有一些
some places we're not sure yet
有一些地方我們還不確定
is it right
是不是正確的
more research needed
需要更多的研究
what is the future
那到底未來
under new climate conditions
在新的氣候條件之下
Those of us who create natural disasters with severe weather like typhoons
我們這些造成自然災害的劇烈天氣像颱風
or good rain
或是好雨
How to change systematically
如何系統性的改變呢
more research is needed
還需要更多的研究
that many
那許多的
Scientists are still working on this
科學家都在這個方面還在持續努力之中
Well, another interesting topic I mentioned at the beginning is typhoons.
那我剛一開始也提到了另外一個有趣的議題是颱風
A symbiosis with the ocean
跟海洋是一個共生體
There is no typhoon without ocean
沒有海洋就沒有颱風
Typhoons are only produced on warm oceans
颱風只會在溫暖的海洋上才會產生
Obviously the ocean is a very important player
顯然海洋是一個非常重要的一個角色
Among our many scientists
在我們的許多科學家
Some research results that have only been discovered in the past few decades
在也是近幾十年才發現的一些研究成果
discovered that the ocean provides powerful conditions
就發現了海洋提供了有力的條件
let the typhoon develop
讓颱風發展
But our typhoon is also very interesting
可是我們颱風也非常的有趣
Typhoons also affect the ocean
颱風也會影響海洋
Because the wind of the typhoon blows on the sea
因為颱風的風吹在海上
Give the ocean very strong this we say kerrik
給海洋非常強的這個我們說切印力
will blow the ocean
會吹動海洋
because the ocean moves too
因為海洋也會移動
This move will flip the ocean
這個移動會翻腳海洋
makes the ocean
使得海洋
We know the ocean temperature is structured like this
我們知道海洋的溫度的結構是這樣
The temperature is getting colder as we go down
越往下去溫度就越來越冷
there's a place on the surface of the ocean that we call the mixed layer
那在海洋表面有一個我們稱為混合層的地方
About tens of meters above the surface of the ocean
大概在海洋的表面數十公尺
Up to a range of 100 meters at most?
最多最多到一百公尺的範圍呢
These places have higher temperatures
這些地方溫度比較高
Then there's the cold sea water
再下來就是很冷的海水了
cold all the way to the bottom of the sea
一路冷到海底
The water on the surface of our oceans may have
我們海洋表面的海水可能有
For example, the temperature of 27, 28 degrees
比如說27、28度的溫度
But it's only 20 degrees below 100 meters
可是到100公尺以下已經只剩20度了
when the typhoon blows across the ocean
當颱風吹過海洋的時候
the ocean will turn
海洋會翻角
That's because of the wind
那是因為風的影響
The sea caused by this typhoon
那這一個颱風引起的海洋
Up and down exchange of upper seawater
上層的海水的上下的交換
This process of mixing corners
這一個混合的翻角的過程
will bring the cold sea water up
就會把冷的海水帶上來
After the typhoon cools down
颱風這一冷卻之後
maybe a few degrees
可能會好幾度
Then the sea temperature that was originally favorable for the development of typhoons
那這個本來有利颱風發展的海溫
not enough
就不夠了
after not enough
不夠之後呢
The typhoon will weaken or even dissipate
颱風就會減弱甚至就會消散
Then you can see this example
那各位可以看到這個例子
This is a typhoon that happened in 2001
這是發生在2001年的一個颱風
That typhoon is called Typhoon Billis.
那這個颱風叫比利斯颱風
Maybe you are not familiar with
可能大家比較不熟悉
But this typhoon is very interesting
可是這個颱風非常有趣
Our first in Taiwan
我們台灣的第
The second one, just mentioned the first modernized radar was on July 23, 1996
第二顆,剛剛講第一顆現代化雷達是1996年7月23色的
The second one was set in July 2001
第二顆呢,就設在2001年的7月
The one located on Green Island
那一顆設在綠島
After that radar is set up,
那一顆雷達設好之後
less than a month
不到一個月呢
I have experienced it, experienced the strongest new typhoon in that era
就經歷過了,就經歷一個那一個年代最強的新的颱風
directly across from Green Island
就直接從綠島穿過
Very amazing, this is not something that can be explained by science
非常神奇,這個不是科學可以解釋的
That
那
After this one passed through, everyone saw that he just passed through Green Island
這一個穿過之後,各位看到他剛好穿過綠島
The radar is back
那個雷達也就回了
It took a year to rebuild
那一花一年重建
But
可是
After reconstruction, it was rebuilt with the same standard, and no typhoon of the same intensity has passed by until now.
重建之後用同樣的標準重建,到現在再也沒有同樣強度的颱風經過
survived until now
存活到現在
It's just unfortunate that he
就是很不巧的,他
He has a design limit
他有一個設計的極限
Because the cost of designing a radar that can withstand stronger winds is much higher
因為要設計可以抗更強的風的雷達的成本,高非常的多
So he designed to say this
所以他就設計說這個
should
應該
There is a small chance that a typhoon will pass by
機率很小的颱風會經過
It turned out just right
結果剛好
They were all encountered within a month of completion.
都是在完工之後一個月內就被遇到了
But it's been fine since then
可是之後到現在就沒事了
This typhoon is back
這個颱風回來
Before the typhoon passed by, he did not reach Taiwan
在颱風他經過還沒到台灣之前
Please tell us about the satellite data
各位看到衛星的資料告訴我們
The temperature of the water on the east side of his typhoon passing by
他的颱風路過的東側還水的溫度
massive reduction
大量的降低
What is the extent of this reduction?
這個降低的程度呢
Basically can reach 4 to 5 degrees
基本上可以到達4到5度
So the whole sea is cold
所以整海水都冷掉了
Then the typhoon will weaken slightly once he cools down
那他一冷掉颱風就會稍微減弱
In other words
換句話說呢
We the ocean are playing for us
我們海洋在幫我們扮演
A machine of nature that adjusts the intensity of typhoons
自然的一個調整颱風強度的機器
The ocean automatically tells the typhoon to brake
海洋自動就叫颱風要煞車
On the one hand, the ocean provides energy to make the typhoon grow
海洋一方面提供能量叫颱風成長
But when the typhoon rises to a certain level
可是當颱風漲到一個程度的時候
The effect of this cold water of the ocean
海洋的這一個冷水的作用
I will tell the typhoon to speak slowly
又會叫颱風說慢一點
don't get stronger
不要再更強
Then this function is also a very interesting
那這個作用也是一個非常有趣的
Scientific question
科學問題
What if this effect is not well understood?
那這個作用如果了解不夠透徹呢
It is difficult for you to predict how strong the typhoon will develop
你就很難預測颱風強度能發展到什麼程度
That's us too, but our ocean observation data is relatively limited.
那也是我們 可是我們海洋的觀測資料是比較有限的
Therefore, our prediction of the intensity of the typhoon is also affected by this ocean factor.
所以我們颱風的強度的預測也受到這一個海洋的因素的影響
I have a colleague who has done a really good job with this research on colleagues
我有一個同事 在同事相關的這個研究做得非常的好
I have a joint research with him
我跟他有一個共同的研究的成果
What about my colleague, Teacher Lin Yiyi?
那我的這位同事林一一老師呢
He also noted that he used a large number of satellite observations
他也注意到他用很多大量的衛星的觀測
can tell where the ocean is warmer and thicker
可以知道海洋哪些地方比較暖 那比較厚
If the temperature of the ocean is thicker, the ocean is thicker
如果海洋的這個溫 比較厚的海洋 比較厚的話
The typhoon has less disturbance to it
颱風對它的干擾就比較小
Because the cold sea water cannot come up in the deep place
因為那個冷海水在很深的地方上不來
Under such ocean conditions, the typhoon may become very strong.
那這樣的海洋條件的話 颱風就可能可以增強的非常的強
So this one example here is telling us that the ocean
那這一個例子 這裡就在告訴我們海洋
Some places are very warm and thick, some places are colder
有些地方特別暖特別厚 有些地方比較冷
red is warm
紅色就是暖厚
since 2003
在2003年以來
There is a typhoon causing serious disaster in Busan, South Korea
有一個造成在韓國的釜山嚴重災難的颱風
It was developed to the strongest stage
它當初發展到最強的階段
when passing through this area
就是在經過這個區域的時候
in the pacific
在太平洋上
Just passed a very, very warm warm water
剛好經過一個非常非常暖的暖水
the warm zone we call the ocean
我們稱為海洋的暖沃區
Teacher Lin Yiyi noticed that
林一一老師就注意到說
This typhoon called MIMI
這個叫做MIMI的颱風
Typhoon MIMI is passing through this area
MIMI的颱風就在經過這一區的時候
It's as strong as a triple jump
它的強度好像在三級跳一樣
It changed from a typhoon of the first category to a second category
它從第一級的颱風變第二級
Change the third level, the fourth level, to the fifth level yellow
變第三級 第四級 到第五級黃色的
it just passes through this area
它就剛好通過這個區域
Because the ocean is thick enough
因為這海洋夠厚
So that natural restriction can't happen
所以那個自然的限制作用發生不了了
Because the warm water is blocked very below
因為暖水被擋在很下面
In the deep sea below 100 meters
100公尺以下的深海裡面
so it grows
所以它就長起來了
This particle happens to be a few years later
這個粒子剛好在幾年後
There is a very good proof
有一個非常好的印證
This proof happened in 2005
這個印證就發生在2005年
very different
非常不一樣
one in the south of america
在美國南邊的一個
everyone is familiar with
各位都熟悉的
This is the giant peak called Catalina
這叫卡特里納的巨峰
This giant peak first landed
這個巨峰當初登陸
This New Europe-faced area
這個紐歐臉的地區
caused thousands of casualties
造成很大的數千人的傷亡的死亡
This giant peak is also God's will
這個巨峰說來也是天意
really unfortunate
真的是很不幸
When this giant peak just passed by here
這個巨峰剛好經過這裡的時候
It was originally just a second-level giant peak.
本來只是一個第二級的巨峰而已
But just in this season
可是剛好在這個季節
America has an ocean current
美國有一股洋流
This ocean current we call lasing current
這個洋流我們稱為套流
The larger scope of this set of flow is from this side
這個套流更大的範圍是從這邊流上來
Then on the Cuban side will pass here
然後在古巴西邊會通過這邊
up through the east side of florida
經過佛羅里達的東邊往上離開
This current is called the Mexican Pill Current
這一股洋流叫做墨西哥丸流
that is a warm current
那是一股暖流
warm current from the south
從南邊來的暖流
This warm current in this Atlantic Ocean
在這個大西洋上的這股暖流
usually flow like this
平常是這樣流動的
But this warm current has an instability
可是這個暖流它有一個不穩定
occasionally twists out
偶爾會曲折出來
and will come out
然後會繞出來
Sleeve flow
繞出來的部分就被稱為套流
it becomes a loop
它成為一個loop
Our Chinese translation complete flow
我們中文翻成套流
just at that time it came out
剛好在那個時候它繞出來了
It's like Mazu went around
好像馬祖繞進一樣
around the gulf of mexico
繞到墨西哥灣
would have been gulf of mexico
本來墨西哥灣
The sea water of this bay
這一個灣的海水
is very very shallow mixed layer
是非常有非常淺的混合層
That is to say
也就是說
the water is cold under it
它下面水很冷
easy to run up to
很容易跑到上面來
So most typhoons pass through the Gulf of Mexico
所以多數的颱風在經過墨西哥灣的時候
weakens soon
很快就減弱
But that time I just met this warm cow passing by
可是那一次剛好遇到這個暖牛經過
So this typhoon is blessed here
所以這個颱風在這邊被加持了
The result of this blessing
這個加持的結果
it goes from level two to level five
它從二級升級到第五級
Just leave this warm cow when you are at your strongest
就在最強的時候才離開這個暖牛
then slowly fades away
然後慢慢又減弱
But it landed at level 4
可是它在四級的時候就登陸了
Originally the United States designed this one
當初美國設計這一個
Time to watch out for this one in New Orleans Beachview
New Orleans Beachview的這個提防的時候
It is designed to resist...
它是設計可以抗...
Category 3 hurricane
三級的颶風
Mainly because the hurricane in this place can't be that strong
主要就是因為這個地方的颶風不可能那麼強
will weaken
都會減弱
But that year happened to encounter this warm current
可是那一年就剛好遇到這個暖流
So the ocean is so important
所以海洋太重要了
Of course this unfortunate
那當然這個不幸的
This accident is the match of fate
這個意外就是這種因緣際會的搭配
In addition to the excavation in the New European Union area
加上這個紐歐聯地區的地挖
Then we must rely on this precaution to protect
然後必須靠這一個提防來保護
But watch out for the last three places where the embankment breaks
可是提防最後有三個地方潰堤
So the whole city is buried under the flood
所以整個都市被大水給掩埋的情況
on our east coast
在我們的東岸呢
In fact there is a similar one
事實上也有一個類似的一個
characteristic ocean currents
特徵的洋流
This ocean current we all know is
這個洋流我們都知道的是
our black grass
我們的黑草
This black grass is passing through the east side of Taiwan to the north
這黑草是經過台灣的東側往北
but
不過
What about his organization?
他的這個組織呢
main
主要
It is obvious here that in this area
這裡明顯的是在這一帶
What about the black grass?
那這個黑草呢
right now we
我們現在
It is suspected that Typhoon Nali was around here in the first place.
懷疑當初造成納利颱風在這邊環繞的
This one Nali can be here in September
這一個納利可以在這邊9月份可以
Survival last affects Taiwan
存活最後影響台灣
It may be closely related to passing through the black grass
就跟經過黑草可能也是息息相關
So if we want to understand typhoons
所以如果我們想要了解颱風
Not only the atmosphere but also the ocean
還不能只知道大氣還要知道海洋
Both must pass
這兩個都要通
may be more precise
可能才能更精確的
Can judge how it will develop in the future
可以判斷它未來怎麼發展
even predict it
甚至預測它
those are some examples
那這些都是一些例子
Then at the end of today, I will introduce to you
那我在今天的最後會跟大家介紹
How can we use the modern scientific method
我們怎麼透過現代化的科學方法
to enhance our understanding of the issue
去加強我們對這個問題的理解
Ok, the last question for today's first period
好今天的第一階段的最後一個問題
Many people must want to ask
很多人都一定想問的
Can a typhoon be reformed?
颱風可不可以改造
how
怎樣
You may have heard many such sayings.
那各位可能也聽過很多這樣的一些說法
that in fact we are in
那事實上在我們在
National Geographic Discovery
National Geographic Discovery
There are topics discussing whether the typhoon can be transformed
都有專題在討論颱風能不能改造
Is the answer Yes or No?
那答案是Yes還是No呢
I wrote an article for Scientist magazine in 2006
我在2006年幫科學人雜誌寫了一篇文章
talk about this
談這個問題
In simple terms
那簡單來講呢
yes there are many different ideas
是有很多不同的想法
Some of these ideas
那這些想法裡面有些
scientifically based
有科學根據的
Most of them have scientific basis
大部分都有科學根據
But in essence
可是實質上呢
It's something that our human technology can't do at present.
都是目前我們人類科技做不到的
So I listed him as a little bit
所以我幫他列為有一點
close to sci-fi
接近科幻的層次
But it's a good idea
可是這理念都是不錯的
let me talk to you
我跟大家聊一下
You can go back and think about it
各位可以回去再想看看
do you have any ideas
你有沒有什麼想法可以
what to do
要怎麼
change typhoon
改變颱風
In America since the 1960s
在美國呢從1960年代
From 1980 to 20 years
到1980到20年期間
proposed an idea
提出了一個構想
A large research project called
一個很大的研究計畫叫
Broken plan
破颱計畫
Broken Wind Project
破風計畫
What about this shattering plan?
那這個破風的計畫呢
It was proposed by a group of excellent scientists
是一群很優秀的科學家提出來了
their idea is to say
他們的想法就是說
What if we can be around the typhoon?
我們如果能在颱風的周圍呢
to do artificial rainfall
去做人工的降雨的活動
artificial rain
人工蒸雨
Just sprinkle some chemical camp and so on
就是灑點化營等等
Let the typhoon around
讓颱風周圍的
The atmosphere condenses and rains at the periphery of the typhoon in advance
大氣提前在颱風外圍的地方就凝結降雨
After the typhoon came in, the water vapor condensed outside ahead of time
颱風進來了水蒸氣提前在外面都凝結掉之後
The eyewall inside the typhoon was wiped out.
颱風裡面那個眼牆就被乾掉了
Or we say being chocked
或是我們說被chock
suffocated
被窒息了
it has no water vapor
它就沒有水蒸氣了
it will dissipate
它就會消散
If the main winds of the typhoon are all turning outside
颱風的主要的風如果都在外面轉的話
like an ice skater he was spinning really fast
就好像溜冰選手他本來轉得很快
when he opened his hand
他把手張開的時候
Because of the conservation of absolute foot momentum
因為絕對腳動量的保守
The speed of his entire rotation slows down.
他整個旋轉的速度就減慢了
The idea is entirely based on physics
構想是完全有物理根據的
But they have been flying planes for more than ten years
可是他們飛了十幾年的飛機
I went into the typhoon and sprinkled a lot of these phones
到颱風裡面去灑了非常多的這些電話
This so-called agglomeration
營等等的這一個所謂的凝結合
to help the typhoon rain on the periphery
來幫助颱風在外圍降雨
Finally, analyze the result
最後把這個結果加以分析
to the early 1980s
到1980年代初期
The United States finally invited a very famous scientist
美國最後請了一個非常有名的科學家
Zhu Zhiying
朱智英
Made a committee to see if it worked after all
使了一個委員會來驗證說到底有沒有用
As a result, the research report showed that
結果那個研究報告顯示
they can't prove
他們沒辦法證明說
with or without home
有家跟沒家
Does the strength of the typhoon affect
颱風的強度有沒有影響
So that project ended up being discontinued.
所以那個計畫最後就停止了
Then this idea will stay in this city forever
那這個構想就永遠停留在這個城市
because we want to be efficient
因為我們要有效的
with limited aircraft resources
用有限的飛機資源
To transform the entire radius of hundreds of kilometers
去改造整個這麼數百公里半徑範圍的
Typhoon rainfall in a large environment
一個大環境的颱風降雨
Actually that cost a lot
事實上那個所費很高
and existing tools are not capable of implementing at scale
而且現有的工具也沒辦法大量實施
so can't do it
所以做不到
Unless of course the only way to do it is to do it in the computer
除非那當然唯一能做到是在電腦裡面去做
That might be possible, but it's practically impossible at the moment.
那或許有可能可是實質上目前還做不到
Another very interesting idea
還有一個很有趣的構想呢
The idea is this
這個構想是這樣
We also have some very interesting active surfactants
我們還有一些很有趣的一些活性的界面劑
These interface agents are called Sephechon in English
這些界面劑英文叫Sephechon
And these interface agents
而且這些界面劑
It's just a thin layer of ink on the sea
就是鋪在海上的一層薄薄的油墨
These inks if you can spread it out to sea
這些油墨如果你能把它鋪到海上的話
Our water will be separated from the air
我們的水就會跟空氣被隔著阻絕了
it can't evaporate anymore
它沒辦法再蒸發了
Then the atmosphere will not get a source of water vapor
那大氣就得不到水氣的來源
That typhoon might not last
那颱風就可能撐不下去了
In the computer, you can experiment and say
在電腦裡面可以實驗說
If you block the whole ocean
如果你把整個海洋都阻絕的話
The typhoon will never come out
颱風絕對長不出來
So scientists do experiments
所以科學家就做實驗
throw these on the ocean
在海洋上撲下這一些
And it's eco-friendly, bio-soluble, these
而且是環保的生物性可溶解的這些
Surfection's active surfactants
surfection的這些活性界面劑
But they were stupid and found that they couldn't stop
可是他們傻的結果還是發現擋不住
Because the range of the typhoon is too large
因為颱風的範圍太大了
If you don't give me water here
你這裡不給我水沉深汐
I come from another side
我從別邊來
so never stop
所以永遠擋不住
Unless you completely block the entire sea
除非你把整個大海全部完全封鎖
Then this is definitely except in the virtual world of the computer
那這是肯定除了在電腦的虛擬世界之外
None other than Avatar
除了阿凡達之外也都沒有
have a chance to do it
有機會做得到
it's an interesting topic
這是一個很有趣的議題
i have a scientist
我有在科學家
keep exploring
繼續探索
Of course this is the domain of the most avant-garde research
當然這是最前衛的研究的範疇
To really transform the typhoon
要真的去改造颱風
Maybe even more future technologies
或許還要更多更多未來的科技
Another thought is
還有一個想法是
satellite in the sky
用空中的衛星
to collect sunlight
去收集太陽光
concentrate sunlight on
把太陽光集中反射到
Some specific areas of typhoons
颱風的某些特定的區域
heat up that area
讓那個地區加熱
then look forward to say
然後期待說
The typhoon will go in a certain direction
颱風會往某個特定的方向前進
Do not come to Taiwan but go to the Philippines
不到台灣來而去菲律賓
right
對不對
this
這個
This is of course very very
這當然是非常非常的
unethical and immoral behavior
不倫理不道德的行為
so
所以
Of course I was just joking
當然我剛剛是開玩笑的
So that's a whole other topic
所以這是一個另外一個議題
Someone brought this up
那這個都有人提出來
Some people have thought about it
也有人去想過
That's not possible with current technology
那目前的科技還做不到
but for us humans
可是給我們人類
From a scientist's point of view
從科學家的角度來講
from a scientific point of view
用科學的角度去
attract us
吸索咱們
Some ways to fundamentally remove the typhoon problem
根本的把颱風問題移除的一些辦法
However, in fact, these methods are not currently available.
可是事實上這些辦法目前還不是辦法
just some ideas
就是一些想法
This is my first stage today
這是我今天第一階段
I want to hear everyone's feedback
我想聽看看大家的回饋
we go to the second stage
我們再進入第二階段
let's have a beer
來喝杯啤酒吧
Sorry, Zhongyuan Institute did not provide
對不起 中原院沒有提供
Okay, let's just imagine drinking a beer
好 我們就想像喝了一杯啤酒
spirit again
精神又來了
I just talked to you about the disaster caused by the typhoon
我剛剛跟大家談了颱風的災害
I also know the typhoon
也認識了颱風
if that's not enough
如果還不夠的話
There is a book you can read
有一本書各位可以去看
Then I introduced the typhoon may be related to the concept of climate
那我介紹的颱風可能跟氣候的觀念
Talk to the ocean at last about the makeover
跟海洋最後談到改造
Are there any current Phase 1 questions?
有沒有目前第一階段的問題
Not bad, obviously everyone absorbed
不錯 顯然大家都吸收了
that's good yes
那好 Yes
min GPA o Canada min GPA o Toronto
MING PAO CANADA MING PAO TORONTO
right
對
Um
嗯
That's a broader issue than a typhoon.
那是比較廣義的不是針對颱風的議題了
That
那
that basically
那個基本上
Thanks for reminding me
謝謝你提醒我
What about the whole concept of a slideshow?
那一個投影片的整個概念呢
It is part of the entire disaster prevention system of the entire government
是在現在整個政府的整個防災體系裡面一個
A more comprehensive part of thinking
全比較全面性在思考的一環
that other
那其他
They are directly related to typhoons
都直接是可以跟颱風比較可以有關
That
那
The whole of our environment mentioned in it
裡面提到的這個整個我們的環境
The changes in society itself include us in Taiwan, which is an obvious feature that includes
社會本身的變遷包括我們在台灣這是一個很明顯的特徵就是包括
Aging and declining birthrate
高齡化跟少子化
Maybe he is emphasizing the concept of economic activities
那可能他比較強調的是跟經濟活動的觀念
and society as a whole
還有整個社會的
For example, I think it should be, he may be emphasizing that
比如說應該我覺得應該他可能是要強調的就是說
society has one
社會的有一個
a characteristic of aging
年齡老化的一個特徵
So society is changing during this process
那在這個過程裡面社會在改變
The residents of these different age groups
那這些不同的年紀層的這個居民
He's adapting to various disasters, maybe his conditions, etc.
他在適應各種災害的或許他的條件等等
different must be considered
也不一樣都必須考量
Yes, of course the comparison I just mentioned
是 那當然這個我剛剛提的比較
a bit more general
比較籠統一點
But he is the whole big country
不過他都是整個大的國土
One related to security and disaster issues
跟安全跟災害議題的一個
part of
的一環
So to think more broadly
所以要被更廣泛來思考
good
好
Yes one more question
Yes 再來一題
good yes
好 是
then ask first
那首先請教
Typhoon actually my feeling
颱風事實上我的感覺
He should have the function of energy balance
他應該是有能量的平衡的作用
He takes the heat from a place closer to where he eats it
他把熱量從比較接近吃到的地方
north half
往北半
Then if we block the typhoon
那如果我們把颱風擋掉的話
Will it force our atmosphere
會不會強迫我們的大氣
The energy gap between the two sides is getting bigger and bigger
兩邊的能量差越來越大
In the end, a more terrible storm came out
到最後才是一個更可怕的風暴出來
that's a very good question
這是非常好的問題
I will add to you
我跟大家補充一下
Just now this is an expert's question
剛剛這是內行的問題
our whole
我們整個
On Earth we know that the sun heats up more unevenly
在地球我們知道太陽的加熱是比較不均勻的
So it's warmer on average in the tropics.
所以在熱帶地方平均來講是比較暖的
Heating by more radiation from the sun
因為太陽比較多的輻射的加熱
The higher the tail, the less
那比較高尾度就比較少
In fact, scientists have analyzed
那事實上有科學家分析
That is, if our climate is to stabilize
就是我們的氣候要達到穩定的話
This energy must be redistributed
這個能量一定要重新分布
reach an equilibrium
達到一個平衡態
Although the south is still
雖然南邊還是
The equator is still warm
赤道還是比較暖
But at least it's not getting warmer
可是至少它不會越來越暖
or the base is getting warmer
或是基地越來越暖
Then this effect depends on the delivery of a lot of air flow
那這個作用就要靠很多的空氣流動的輸送
including ocean transport
包括海洋的輸送
to adjust for temperature differences
來調整溫度的差異
It is unstable when the difference is too large.
那差異太大的時候是不穩定的
its atmosphere is unstable or the ocean
它的大氣是不穩定的或海洋
that if
那如果
The presence of that typhoon did play an important role.
那颱風的存在的確扮演了一個很重要的角色
It happened to be mentioned in that book
在那本書剛好有提到
Can help with this energy delivery
可以幫忙做這個能量的輸送
So if this is more artificially changed
所以如果這個有比較用人工的方式去改變
is capable of disrupting the existing equilibrium of our climate
是可以破壞我們氣候現有的平衡態
then you must
那你肯定必須
It's going to find a new balance point
它要去尋找新的平衡點
Well, that does make a difference
那這個的確會產生不同的影響
to what extent
那至於影響到什麼程度
Will there be other different changes?
會不會有其他不同的變化的
What about the weather for these so-called special freaks?
這些所謂特殊的怪胎的天氣出現呢
In fact, there is research
事實上是有在研究的
good question thanks
這是好問題 謝謝
ok my last question for phase one
好我第一階段的最後一個問題
Please tell me, if you say
請教喔那如果說
Someday science has its way in science
哪一天科學在科學方面有辦法
That is to block the typhoon
就是說去阻擋颱風
Will this cause sweating?
那這樣會不會造成大汗災
Thanks
謝謝
Because the typhoon will bring abundant quantity
因為颱風會帶來豐沛的一量
If there is a scientific way to stop the typhoon
那如果真的科學有辦法去阻止颱風
no typhoon
沒有颱風的
Will the whole earth be a disaster of sweat?
那整個地球會不會是大汗災
good question
好問題
let me in fact we earth have very, very many
讓我在事實上我們地球有非常非常多
not a typhoon
不是颱風
But it's also a convective system that produces a lot of rainfall.
可是也是造很大降雨的對流系統
The convective is the convective rain that rises from the air
那這些對流的就是空氣上升的這些對流降雨
These systems may have a smaller range
這些系統可能它的範圍比較小
only tens of kilometers
只有數十公里
range of several kilometers
幾公里的範圍
they don't really rain
他們也不實在下雨
The typhoon is one of the few cases
颱風是其中的一個少數個案
but it's very organized
可是它是非常有組織性的
tens to hundreds of kilometers
把數十到數百公里的
This is a monster that combines airflow and rainfall
這一個氣流跟降雨都集合在一起的一個怪物好了
is really a monster
就是真的是一個monster
If this thing does not exist when
如果這個東西不存在的時候
Maybe nature has other ways of adjusting
或許大自然也有其他的調整的因應方式
how to deal with it
那到底怎麼因應
I'll get to that shortly
我剛待會就會談到這一點
So after we drink these four or five glasses
所以在我們喝完這四、五杯之後
let's continue
我們就繼續吧
Then I'll just get to your point from here
那我就從這裡剛好待會會到你這一點
In fact, we all know the typhoon forecast
那事實上我們也都知道颱風預測
actually not that good
事實上沒有那麼好
You can also hear that you are sometimes very demanding
各位也可以偶爾會聽到大家有時候很苛求
would think why can't we do better
會覺得說我們為什麼不能做得更好
Why can't weather forecasts be more accurate?
氣象的預測為什麼不能更精確
You clearly said you would log in, why didn't you come?
明明說會登陸的為什麼沒來
Then put a day off and said afterwards
然後就擺放了一天假然後事後說
Ask us to make up driving, make up passengers and make up shifts
要我們來補駕 補客補班
Of course that's a very crazy idea
當然那是非常瘋狂的想法
But basically, you can see this example
不過基本上呢 各位可以看這個例子
Typhoon Maeji 2010
梅姬颱風2010年
This one caused heavy rain in Suao. Do you remember this typhoon?
這一個造成蘇澳下大雨 各位記得這個颱風呢
it goes through the philippines
它經過菲律賓
At that time, predictions around the world were very different.
那時候全世界各地的預測 非常的不一樣
The north side of the South Park is very inconsistent
南園北側 非常不一致
wait until after it passes the philippines
等到它經過菲律賓之後
Worldwide forecasts are also completely different
全世界的預測也是完全不一樣
No one knows Mo Zhong I
沒有人知道 莫忠一世
This is the computer's prediction
這是電腦的預測
don't know where he's going
不知道他要去哪
Then this highlights the typhoon forecast
那這就凸顯了颱風預測
there are many difficulties
是有很多的困難
who do you trust
你要相信誰呢
In this example, if you choose the middle, you are right.
在這個例子裡面 你如果選中間的話就對了
he ended up like this
他最後是這樣上來
Basically, when he was in the process
那基本上呢 他在這個過程的時候
While here, the typhoon is raining heavily
在這裡的時候 颱風在下大雨
also very strange
也是很莫名其妙
But if you understand that this is the role of Qiutai
可是如果你了解這是秋台的作用的時候
you can understand
你就可以比較理解
Why is there rainfall caused by this co-organization?
為什麼會有這個共辦的作用造成的降雨
But if this path is different, then the shape of the rainfall
可是這個路徑如果不一樣 那降雨的形態
must change completely
一定完全改變
Therefore, the entry forecast of typhoon
所以颱風的入境的預測
I have always wanted to understand how typhoons change
一直是要了解颱風怎麼變化的一個
the most basic question
最基本的一個問題
Speaking of which, we will involve
說到這裡我們就牽扯到
I'm sorry this one hasn't turned it into Chinese yet
對不起這一張還沒有把它變成中文
The progress of our entire science now
我們現在的整個科學的進展
is to digitize the problem
是把這個問題都數位化
We use computers to predict typhoons
我們用電腦來預測颱風
But this is definitely far beyond
可是這絕對是遠超乎
What we now call the Dimension Doushu
我們現在所謂的指維斗數
You will know when you enter the generated horoscope
各位輸入生成八字就會知道
possible future
各位未來可能的
or short-term or long-term development of fate
或短期或長期的命運的發展
This is indeed based on our understanding of the entire
這個的確是根據我們所理解的整個
The basic operation of nature, physics, chemistry and mathematics
大自然物理化學數學基本運作的
some fundamental principles
一些最根本的原理
Including simply speaking Newton's laws of motion
包括簡單來講牛頓的運動定律
laws of thermodynamics etc.
熱力學定律等等
to understand the fluids in our atmosphere
去了解流體在我們的大氣裡面
how to change
要怎麼的變化
take all these processes
把這一些過程全部把它
with we can
用我們可以
Mathematical way to do it
可以做的數學方法去做
Solutions of Differential Equations
微分方程式的解
then go find out its answer
然後去找出它的答案
Then we construct this thing called numerical mode
那我們建構這個東西叫數值模式
if you can tell me this fluid
你如果能告訴我這個流體
Current state
現在的狀態
I may be able to predict the future state
我可能可以預測未來的狀態
What about the entire computer in the world?
那全世界的這個整個電腦呢
progress
的進展呢
has a large level
有很大的一個層面
are working together to solve this problem
都在配合解決這個問題
as long as the computer every other year
只要電腦每隔一年
We all know that there is an electricity
我們都知道有一個電力
it will increase the speed of its operation
它會增加它的運算的速度
degree of change
一變的程度
that's almost working with us
那幾乎就是在配合我們
Development of Atmospheric Computing
大氣的計算的發展
five years ago
在五年前呢
In Japan there is a thing called Earth Simulator
在日本有一個叫地球模擬器
It's as big as a rain bomb
它就像一個小機雨彈那麼大
that's all in operation
那都是在運算
It was the fastest computer in the world at the time
那時候是全世界最快的電腦
Its floating point operation speed per second
它的每一秒的浮點運算速度
is 40 multiplied to the power of 12
是40乘以時的12次方
so very very fast
所以非常非常的快
terabytes the flux every second
每一秒就terabytes the flux
The updated computer is now in the United States
那現在更新的電腦是在美國
Then the US won him back
後來美國又把他贏回來了
back face
反回面子
in Tennessee
在田納西
What about the new system in the United States?
美國的那一套新的系統呢
about fifty times that
大概是這個五十倍
Now it is the Flux of two times ten to the fifteenth power
現在是二乘以十的十五次方的Flux
then it is faster
那它是更快了
But most of them are doing this calculation
不過很大都是在做這個計算
Understanding Changes in Our Earth's Climate
了解我們地球氣候的變化
But there is a fundamental problem with this calculation
可是這個計算裡面有一個很根本的問題
You may have heard
各位可能也聽過了
called this effect
叫做叫做這個效應
effect called chaos
叫混沌的效應
Then if we have any uncertainty about the initial state
那我們如果對初始的狀態有任何不確定的話
Future predictions are likely to get worse and worse
未來的預測是有可能越差越多的
just a little bit
就是差一點點
Ten millimeters are a thousand miles away
十支毫米差支千里
It can be completely different in the end
就可以最後的完全不一樣
Then this feature was discovered by a famous scholar
那這個特徵有一個著名的學者發現的
That's Edward Lorenz
就是Edward Lorenz
What about this teacher I studied in my school days?
那這位我以前念書時代學習的一位老師呢
He actually has been in the past few years ago
他事實上一直都是在過去幾年前
in his world
在他世界上
In fact, in the past few years, it is said that they were still in the final list of the Nobel Prize in Physics.
事實上前幾年據說都是還在物理諾貝爾獎的最後的 final list 裡面
It's a pity, of course, that he died before he won the award.
那當然很可惜他在還沒得獎之前去死了
But this is a very large research contribution
不過這是非常大的一個研究的貢獻
That effect is also called the butterfly effect.
那這個效應也叫蝴蝶效應
It makes it very difficult for us to forecast the weather or typhoon
就讓我們預報天氣或颱風變得非常的困難
Because we have no idea what a typhoon looks like in the first place
因為我們根本不知道颱風一開始長什麼樣子
That
那
because of this problem
因為這個問題呢
I've just been working on a research project for the past few years and I'm going to wrap up with you today with this project
我剛好在過去幾年從事了一個研究計畫我今天就以這個計畫來跟大家收尾
The key to this is that we need better data to improve our typhoon predictions
那這個的關鍵呢就是我們需要更好的資料來改進我們對颱風的預測
However, the data around the typhoon are very limited.
可是在颱風的周遭資料是非常有限的
Then I just mentioned that we have
那我剛剛提到我們有
radar
雷達
There are satellites in the sky to assist us
天空有衛星都在輔助我們
The radar has its limit because the radar may be able to do what he does
那雷達有他的極限因為雷達可能可以他的這個他所
Electromagnetic waves
電磁波
in the atmosphere
在大氣裡面
It may be able to detect atmospheric features within two to three hundred kilometers
它可能是可以探測兩三百公里以內的大氣特徵
So when the typhoon approaches
所以颱風靠近的時候
You can tell where it's raining by looking at the radar
各位看雷達就可以知道哪裡在下雨
very useful
非常有用
But if the typhoon is farther away
可是如果颱風在遠一點
you can't even see
你看都看不到
Satellites are hundreds of kilometers from us to 7800 kilometers
衛星從我們數百公里七百八百公里的
This orbiting satellite reaches the so-called 36,000 kilometers
這一個繞級衛星到所謂的三萬六千公里的
This geostationary satellite is also monitoring the characteristics of our atmosphere
這個同步衛星也在監控我們的大氣的特徵
Then these waves through different batteries
那這些透過不同的電池波
microwave, etc.
微波等等的訊號
visible light infrared
可見光 紅外線
The atmospheric temperature and other information generated by various signals
各種訊號去繁衍出來的大氣的溫度等等訊息
It also tells us the location of typhoons, etc.
也告訴我們颱風的位置等等的分布
But the key to a typhoon is how the wind blows
可是颱風關鍵它的風怎麼吹
These ways we call panning
這些我們所謂的搖測的方式
There is no way to measure it very accurately.
都沒辦法測得很精確
That makes our initial judgment on the typhoon
那就使得我們對颱風的初始的判斷
there are some errors
有一些的誤差
All make this chaotic effect continue to amplify
都使得這個混沌的效應不斷的放大
Then in order to solve this problem
那為了解決這個問題
scientists will know
科學家就知道了
Use an airplane to detect typhoons
要用飛機去探測颱風
Because this is the only instrument that can put the observation
因為這是唯一可以把觀測的儀器
directly to the vicinity of the typhoon
直接帶到颱風的附近
direct way to measure
直接去量測的方式
However, this method does have a relatively large risk
不過這方式的確是有比較大的風險
let me speed up
我加速一下
That
那
in America
在美國呢
has matured
已經成熟到
They have been since 1970
他們從1970年以來
It has very mature technology
有非常成熟的科技呢
He uses this C-130 transport plane
他用這個C-130的這個運輸機
Or this anti-submarine aircraft called P3
或這個叫P3的反潛機
or this jet
或者是這架噴射機
Fly around the typhoon to detect the typhoon
飛在颱風的周遭去探測颱風
He throws this from the air
他從空中還拋頭這個
The instrument used in the cold test is called Touluosong
涼測的這個儀器叫頭落送
he is in the process of landing
他在降落的過程
The process of transferring from the air to the sea
從空中調到海面的過程
atmospheric information
就可以把大氣的資訊
temperature, humidity, air pressure
溫度、濕度、氣壓
measure out
都量出來
How about measuring wind speed?
那也可以量風速怎麼量呢
Because he will swing with the wind in the air
因為他在空中會隨著風擺動
shift
移位
he can talk to
他可以跟
That's the effect of the wind
那這是受風的影響
he can
他可以
He knows how much the wind will move
他知道怎樣的風會移多少
he has precise
他有精確的
GPS location so it can make an indirect calculation of how the wind is blowing
GPS定位所以它可以製造間接的算出風是怎麼吹的
So it also measures the magnitude and direction of the wind
所以它也量出風的大小跟方向
then we can reconstruct the structure of the typhoon
那我們就可以重建颱風的結構
Especially these two C-130 and P-3 aircraft
特別是這其中的這兩架 C-130 跟 P-3 的飛機
It is usually crossed to the center of the typhoon
它通常是穿到颱風中心打叉
What about after this way of flying?
這樣的飛的方法之後呢
We can create typhoon structures in different four directions
我們就可以製造颱風在不同四個向線的結構
This is the only effective method that can fully resolve the typhoon's characteristics at present
這是唯一目前唯一可以完全解析颱風的特徵的有效方法
The whole world is now only in the Atlantic Ocean that has done such work for a long time
全世界現在只有在大西洋有長期做這樣的工作
Other sunny typhoons can't help
其他的陽面的颱風就沒辦法
Then I will be close to this job
那我跟這個工作會接遠呢
It happened to be in 1991 when I was in graduate school
剛好是在1991年我在念研究所的時候
At that time, my advisor was the author of the book I just talked about.
那時候我的指導教授就是剛剛講的那位書的作者呢
he happened to have he had he was a theorist
他剛好有 他有 他是一個理論學家
He would love to do a big time enlisting his theory
他很想要做一個很大的時間來應徵他的理論
what theory
什麼理論呢
How do typhoons form
颱風是怎麼生形成的
Worldwide in tropical ocean
全世界在熱帶的海洋
three steps five o'clock
三步五時
Just to answer the lady's question
剛好回答剛剛這位女士的問題
There's a lot of convection going on
有非常多的對流在發生
But most of the convection
可是大部分的對流
Clouds grow and it rains
雲朵的成長它會下雨
It usually only has a lifespan of a few hours
它通常都是只有幾個小時的生命期
Dissipate after downloading
下完就消散
Wait for the next cloud to grow
再等下一朵雲長出來
They can't organize into a typhoon
他們沒辦法組織成颱風
only very very few
只有非常非常少的
These convective clouds can become typhoons
這些對流的雲會變成颱風
our world year
我們全世界一年
Only 80 to 90 typhoons can grow
也就只能長出80到90個颱風
Here's another interesting scientific question
這是另外一個有趣的科學問題
what climate is controlling this one 90
是什麼氣候在控制這一個90
the magic number
這個魔術的數字
roughly this is a long number
大致上這是一個長數
80 to 90
80到90
The total number of typhoons in the world in a year
全球的總颱風數一年
that's all
就這麼多而已
Our rations are at Northwest Sun's
我們的配給在西北太陽的
The quota is about 30 or so
配額大概是30左右
That's the most in the world right here
那算是全世界最多的就在這
As for the less important places, there are about a dozen of them here.
那次要的地方呢在這大概有十幾個
here are ten more
這裡有另外十個
just answered there
在那剛剛回答了
Someone asked me why there is no typhoon in Europe when I was eating just now
有剛剛用餐的時候有人問我歐洲為什麼沒有颱風
One is the high tail and the other is the typhoon, both headed westward.
一個是高尾度一個是颱風都往西邊去了
Then the high-tail typhoon was too cold and dissipated.
那到高尾度颱風也太冷就消散了
In addition, it is interesting for you to ask
另外呢各位要問很有趣的是
If you don't have it, it's because you don't have enough
適到沒有那是因為適到缺乏了
The rotation provided by the rotation of our earth is called the Coschel force
我們地球旋轉提供的一個旋轉的這叫科式力
Then this interested friend can go to find the root of this problem
那這個有興趣的朋友可以再去尋求這個問題的根源
But there is no here, so why?
可是這裡也沒有那又是為什麼
The sea temperature here is relatively cold, so there are no typhoons
那這裡的海溫比較冷那長不出颱風
Then why is the sea temperature colder here?
那這裡的海溫為什麼比較冷
It just so happens that the ocean current over there has the eternal current over there
剛好那邊的洋流在那邊有永生流
The sea water rising from the bottom of the sea has completely cooled this side
從海底冒出來的海水把這邊完全冷卻了
The sea temperature here is about three to five degrees lower.
這裡的海溫低了大概低三到五度
Much lower here even in his summer
這邊低很多 即使是在他的夏天一樣很低
why not here
那這裡為什麼沒有
Ok this is our Homework for today
好這是我們今天的 Homework
Homework, please find the answer
家庭作業 請大家去找一找答案
Why is there no one here, okay?
為什麼這邊沒有 好不好
ok i'm back here
好那我回到這裡
Then my advisor wants to know why typhoons grow here
那我的指導教授想要知道颱風為什麼在這邊會長出來
He has a theory, so he decides to test it out.
他有理論 那就決定去驗證
That's when the only typhoon grows
那這是唯一颱風長出來的時候
This place is still very close to mainland Mexico.
這個地方呢 還離陸地墨西哥很近
So we can take the plane to Mexico to detect the typhoon
所以我們可以把飛機拍到墨西哥去探測颱風
Then it is difficult here because in the wild ocean
那在這裡就很難了 因為在荒洋大海上
It's also very difficult here
這裡也非常的困難
So, I just happened to be playing the role of volunteer
所以呢 我當初剛好就扮演志願者的角色
Just go to this event to answer this question
就去參加這個活動 要去回答這個問題
Then our design is like this
那我們的設計是這樣
This has a theory, you have to prove it
這個有理論 你要去應證
You should prove that you can only prove that the theory is wrong
你應證其實只能應證理論是不是錯的
You can't prove the theory is right
你沒辦法應證理論是不是對的
You can only testify whether your answer is positive
你只能應證說 你的答案有沒有積極
In fact, just supporting does not mean that the theory must be correct.
其實只是支持也不表示理論就一定是對的
But if you can just find a different result, the theory is wrong.
可是如果你只要能找到不一樣的結果就表示理論是錯的
There's a lot of cloud development here
這裡有很多雲的發展
We also flew into these clouds to see the typhoon with the Nichiri machine crossed by two planes.
我們用兩架飛機交叉的日理機也飛到這些雲裡面去去看颱風
after reading it
看完之後呢
You can bring back data to know that some of these clouds are missing
你可以帶回資料知道這些雲有的雲不見了
Some clouds turned into typhoons
有些雲變成颱風了
Then you compare the specific characteristics of which clouds become typhoons
那你去比對為什麼哪些雲變成颱風的雲有哪些特定的
Information on the physics of the atmosphere
大氣的物理的資訊
to explain some theories
可以來解釋一些理論
Through this method we conduct experiments
透過這個方法我們來做實驗
Then I happened to be very lucky to participate in this experiment and learned a lot at that time.
那我剛好在那時候很幸運的就去參加了這個實驗學到很多東西
That
那
Didn't this typhoon fly over a typhoon?
這個颱風沒飛過一個颱風呢
This plane flies over a typhoon and will leave a typhoon mark
這個飛機飛過一個颱風就會留下一個颱風的印記
What about this imprint?
那這個印記呢
By then he had 44
到那時候他當初已經有44個了
There are two imprints in it, please see
其中還有兩個印記各位看喔
It grows in a different direction, these two
它長的方向不太一樣這兩個
Why
為什麼
Because he once flew to the southern hemisphere
因為他曾經飛到南半球去
The direction of the typhoon there is just anti-symmetrical to our northern hemisphere
那裡的颱風轉向剛好跟我們北半球是反對稱的
It was the first time in my life that I flew into a typhoon rock that developed from the rain slowly and slowly for three days
這是我生平第一次飛進一個從雨慢慢慢慢三天後發展出來的颱風岩
So it's a rare life experience
所以這是一個很難得的人生的經歷
but most importantly
不過最重要的是
Participate in an experiment where students learn all research methods and tools for free
參加一個實驗在學生免費學習到所有的研究的方法跟工具
Some attitudes or experiences when communicating with scientists are also good
跟科學家交流的一些態度也好或者是一些經驗
Then when I got on the plane for the first time, I thought to myself
那我第一次坐上飛機我心裡在想說
Oh right, why is there no such thing as a flight attendant?
欸對喔怎麼沒有所謂的空姐
In fact, it was all hard work by the technicians.
那事實上都是技術人員硬幫幫的
It's all equipment
裡面全部是設備
i tied myself tight
我把自己綁得很緊
The first sentence is to ask those scientific and technical personnel to say
第一句話就問那些科學技術人員說
Hey, why did you take off before taking a lecture?
欸怎麼還沒做講席就起飛了
What about the safety lecture?
安全講席呢
He said
他說
ah he just told me
啊他就跟我講說
Don't worry
Don't worry
do not worry
不要擔心
no problem
沒有問題
not bad
沒差啦
Because in the typhoon at sea
因為在海上的颱風裡面
in case something goes wrong
萬一真的有什麼故障
then accept fate
那就認命吧
But luckily everything went well
不過幸好一切都很順利
In fact, the United States from 1970 to the present
事實上美國從1970年到現在
There are so many planes that fly into the typhoon
有這麼多飛進颱風的飛機裡面
There is no record of any so-called casualties
都沒有任何所謂的傷亡的記錄
there may have been
之前可能有
no more after that
之後就沒有了
Then if you have such experience
那你如果有這樣的經驗
NOAA
美國的國家大氣海洋總署
Also present you with a certificate
還頒贈你一張certificate
That's one of the baby in my life
那這是我人生寶貝的一張
that's all
就僅此
I believe that few people have the opportunity
我相信在很少人有機會
do such activities
做這樣的活動
I happen to own this one
我剛好擁有這一張
He also wrote some very touching...
他也寫了一些非常感...
can't say touching
不能說感人
some encouraging words
很鼓勵人的一些話說
There is such a Mr. Wu
有這麼一個吳先生
deliberately on that day
在那一天刻意的
purposefully
purposefully
Where can I travel with my senseless spirit?
用無謂的精神穿越到哪裡呢
Go inside the eyeball of some wicked typhoon in the West Indies
在西印度群島的某某邪惡的颱風的眼球裡面去
This selfless orange and hero's devotion
這個無私的橘子跟英雄的奉獻
To us in science is to give him the highest tribute
對我們科學界是要給他最高的致意
oh thank you
喔謝謝
sorry
對不起喔
I just hinted that that wasn't intentional
我剛剛那不是故意的暗示
good
好
after i return to taiwan
我回到台灣之後
Of course, a lot of basic research has been done
當然做了很多基礎的研究
That research just now is not my doctoral thesis either.
剛剛那個研究也不是我的博士論文
It's a process of my experience
就是我一個歷練的過程
I just had a chance later
我剛好後來有機會
I also find this question interesting
我也覺得這個問題很有趣
I'm going to share this with you in the last ten minutes
我在最後的這十分鐘就跟大家分享這個
The experience of developing this scientific research
這個發展這個科學研究的經驗
If there are young friends here today,
如果今天在座還有年輕朋友的話
I also hope to have some inspiration
也希望有一些啟發的作用
That is of course the process of learning
那當然就是說學習的過程
learn a lot of different facets
學到很多不同的面向的東西
Then I just had this chance at last
那最後剛好有這個機會
It's time to let go and make a fortune
就是可以放手一展長財的時候
It just so happens that we put it together
也剛好我們把它組合起來了
Then I was nearly ten years ago
那我在將近十年前
It's been ten years
轉引過了十年了
I organized it almost ten years ago
將近十年前我就組織了
such a new plan
這樣一個新的計畫
Hope NSC Hope Says
希望國科會希望說
We have a focused study
我們有一個重點的研究
There is a relatively breakthrough development
有一個比較突破性的發展
I just come up with ideas that I might be able to do
我就把我可能可以做的構想提出來
I think we have an opportunity to do this kind of detection as well.
我覺得我們也有機會去做這樣的探測
This project is me and a very good colleague
這個計畫呢是我跟我一個很好的同事
made together
共同做起來的
So this job is actually a teamwork
所以這工作其實是一個teamwork
this is very important
這是非常重要的
It took me a lot of time to design this logo to popularize
花了很多時間我設計了這個logo來普遍
besides
還有
I've been thinking about this term for a month
單單這個名詞我想了一個月
I made up the word DustStar
湊出了這個字叫DustStar
Of course it is meaningful when talking about typhoon observation
當然是有意義的在講颱風的觀測
It just so happens that this is dim sum
剛好這是點心
DustStar
DustStar
mentioned on my page
在我的網頁上有提到
like in the night sky of a typhoon
就好像在颱風的夜空
Like the stars that lit up the night sky after we went to observe
我們去觀測之後點亮了夜空的星光一樣
just the intention
剛好就是本意
So our team is still doing well
所以呢我們團隊還長得還不錯
DustStar
DustStar
of course it's a joke
那當然這是笑話
Basically, when I visited the United States in 2007, I felt that the experiment was quite successful
基本上我在2007年在美國有一次訪問的時候覺得實驗做得蠻成功的
Just google to find out that most of the ambassadors are famous
就google一下想知道大使大多有名
It turned out to be a new British rock band.
結果亮出來的是一個英國新的搖滾樂團
But we also took a photo of him looking like this at the gate of National Taiwan University
不過我們也照了一張長這個樣子在台大門口
big breath door
大氣息門口
good
好
what about our plan
那我們這個計畫呢
Basically, we rented a jet plane from Hanxiang in Taichung to detect the typhoon
基本上就是我們跟台中的漢響租了一個噴射機去探測台風
And this detection is strategic
而且這個探測是有策略性的
We're going to find some places where the atmosphere is particularly sensitive to throw our heads
我們就要去找一些大氣特別敏感的地方去拋頭
The instrument just mentioned
剛剛講的那個儀器
I hope this can change our understanding and prediction of typhoons
那希望這個整個可以改變我們對台風的理解跟預測
Then we did another job to measure the results
那我們做了另外一個工作是把我們量到的結果
Even if it is released to any research unit and forecast center in the world, it is not hidden at all
即使發布到全世界任何一個研究單位跟預報中心完全沒有藏起來
Some studies say that the observers use the data for two years before others can use it.
那有的研究是說觀測的人先資料先用兩年別人才能用
Because of the typhoon
因為這個台風的
So this impact is comprehensive and immediate
所以這個影響是全面性的 即時性的
It's a pity to keep it for my own use
有把它留在自己用太可惜了
That's also because we share it on the instant
那也因為我們把它分享在即時
We compile the data in the air and pass it on
我們在空中編飛資料就編傳出去
So it can be taken back to WMO all over the world
那所以可以收回到全世界WMO
all used countries
所有的用的國家
Then maybe our back helmet will be bigger
那可能我們的迴盔會更大
Then it faces many problems
那它要面臨許多的問題
Then I may have an opportunity to introduce this to you later.
那這個可能以後有機會再跟大家介紹
In the blink of an eye, more than nine years have passed
轉眼間過去將九年多來呢
We have detected many, many typhoons
我們已經探測了許許多多的颱風
And most of these typhoons have affected Taiwan
而且多數的這些颱風都影響了台灣
and even the surrounding countries
甚至周邊的各個不同的國家
Everyone can see that this door is all about us in the air
各位可以看到這門一點都是我們在空中
Traces of every instrument ever dropped
曾經丟下來的每個儀器的痕跡
Typhoon passing by
跟這路過的颱風
So all the measuring instruments we've lost so far
那我們到目前一共丟的涼測儀器
nearly a thousand lost
丟了將近一千個
So it's a really big research effort
所以這是一個非常大的研究工作
ongoing
持續在進行之中
Of course, there are also a lot of research rumors
那在這裡面當然也有很多的研究的傳聞
I'll show you some pictures
我給大家看幾張照片
Aren't we always comparing this movement in the air
我們在空中不是一直在比這個動作
This is exactly one of them
這是剛好其中一張
The whole design of our BNFAY is in the Central Meteorological Bureau
我們BNFAY整個design是在中央氣象局
if you know how to get on the web
你如果能知道怎麼上網頁
You can see where our planes go
你都可以看到我們飛機飛到哪
Then measure what data
然後量到什麼資料
Similar to the original satellite and radar pictures
跟當初的衛星跟雷達的圖片
all will be combined
全部都會結合
It's all on the Bureau of Meteorology's webpage
這都在氣象局的網頁
immediately visible
立即都看得到
But there is a specific URL that is
可是有特定的網址是
Not everyone can find it
不見得每個人都找得到
This information will be available to anyone who can find it
如果找得到的人就可以看到這些資訊
The Central Weather Service in their combined
中央氣象局在他們結合了
all the different sources of observation
所有不同的觀測來源
Information about our aircraft
跟我們飛機的資料
He can study and judge the original characteristics of the typhoon
他就可以去研判颱風當初的特徵
Of course, this is only the so-called application part
當然這只是所謂的應用的部分
Our research is like my example
我們的研究就好像我舉例
We call it target observation
我們叫標靶觀測
like the so-called target
就好像標靶的所謂的
A treatment like chemotherapy
化療的一個治療方法一樣
This is called targeted therapy
這個叫 targeted therapy
Our method is called targeted observation
我們的方法叫 targeted observation
to measure
去量測
The most famous example is not a paper I wrote
最著名的例子不是我寫的論文
It was made by the Japanese who worked with us
而是跟我們合作的日本人做出來的
In this example inside
在這個例子裡面
We went to measure various data of this typhoon
我們去量測了這個颱風的各種資料
Three of these are targets
其中這三個是標靶
As a result we found
結果我們發現
Japanese found
日本人發現
Prediction of typhoon direction by the weather model of the whole Japan
整個日本的氣象的模式的預測颱風走向
this is the actual direction
這是實際的走向
After using this data
如果用了這一筆資料之後
Typhoon will turn around
颱風就會轉過來
if not
如果不用呢
The typhoon will come here in the wrong direction
颱風就會走錯方向跑到這裡來
that this one
那這一個
The results of this study probably helped us gain popularity
這個研究結果大概是幫我們打響的知名度
Then I quote a movie I watched before called
那我引用一個以前看過的一部電影叫做
Oh, this one is called honey, there seems to be this movie
喔 這個叫親愛的 好像有這部電影
I made the kid bigger or smaller
我把小孩變大了或變小了
We turned the typhoon
我們把颱風轉向了
Of course it means that we take the typhoon forecast
當然是說我們把颱風的預測
The prediction turned out to be in the direction he should go
預測變準了到他該去的方向
After nearly many years of research
經過將近多年的研究
We found that on average we can reduce the error by about 20%
我們發現大概平均可以減低誤差大概20%
That is to say, the original error may predict the position of the typhoon one day later
也就是說本來的誤差可能預測一天後的颱風的位置
There may be an average error of 100 kilometers between the present and the actual situation
跟現在跟實際可能平均誤差100公里
It can become only 80 kilometers left
它可以變成只剩80公里
not perfect
還不是完美
Because the atmosphere is not perfectly predictable.
因為大氣本來就不是完美可以預測的
However, there are possibilities and results for improvement after the information is available
不過有資料之後有改進的可能跟成效
In 2008 we succeeded because of this
在2008年我們因為這個成功
The whole of Asia has started a new experiment
整個亞洲開啟了一個新的一個實驗
This experiment is through our aircraft
這個實驗是透過我們的飛機
Like inviting the United States to bring two large planes
跟把美國請來兩架大飛機
And Japan also came to fly all the typhoons with a plane
還有日本也來架飛機合飛所有的颱風
So we cross explored
所以我們交叉的探索
At that time, it was equal to the typhoon in the Northwest Pacific in 2008
那時候等於2008年的西北太平洋的颱風
what to explore
探索什麼呢
The life and death of the whole typhoon
整個颱風的生與死
how did it grow
它怎麼長出來的
How did it dissipate in the end
最後怎麼消散
All in this experiment want to answer
都在這個實驗想要去回答
It's never been done before with a test flight
用試駕飛機這是前所未有的
Of course it will require a lot of cooperation
那當然這需要非常大的合作
We can imagine test piloting planes flying together in the sky
我們可以想像試駕飛機在空中同飛
The planes all depart from different countries
飛機都從不同的國家出發
stagger together at last
最後要一起交錯
it's all designed
這都要設計好的
Of course it is impossible to collide
當然不可能撞在一塊
that this team
那這一個團隊
It is developed under the framework of the whole WMO
是在整個WMO的架構下來進展的
There are representatives from various countries
有各個國家的代表
There is a country called Dustar
有一個國家就叫Dustar
Sorry can't use the name Taiwan
對不起不能用台灣這個名字
What about after we do this?
那我們把這個做起來之後呢
There was a famous example
當初有一個很著名的例子
Xinleke Typhoon
叫新樂客颱風
First time in the Pacific Northwest
第一次在西北太平洋
with our planes flying around like this
有我們的飛機這樣環繞飛行
I'm on this plane
我就在這一隻飛機上
Then the US plane flew from Guam
那C美國的飛機從關島飛來
There is another plane from the United States flying over.
還有美國另外一架飛機飛過來
Japanese planes fly over from Tokyo's Atsuki Airport
日本的飛機從東京的阿出奇機場飛過來
the military airport
那個軍用機場飛來
Then go around here and go back, stop at the airport in Okinawa
然後繞到這邊再回去 停在沖繩的機場
Test pilots fly together for the first time in the Pacific Northwest
試駕飛機同飛 第一次發生在西北太平洋
I showed you the simplest example
我給大家看了一個最簡單的例子
This paper has also been published
這個論文也已經發表了
Our observations show
我們的觀測顯示呢
If there is this information
如果有放這個資料呢
The typhoon will turn this way, close to the typhoon
颱風就會往這邊轉 靠近颱風
The computer will predict that the blue line is very close to the actual red line
電腦會預測藍色的線跟實際紅色的線很接近
Forecast from this time
從這個時間開始預測
What if we don't use these observations?
如果不用這些觀測資料呢
it will be green, it's wrong
它就會是綠色的 就找錯了
It's the same here, it's a day later
那這裡也一樣 這是一天之後
Then this photo is
那這個照片是
We always remember to leave a photo before every flight
我們每次起飛前都會記得遺留一張照片
As a souvenir
做紀念
Then the In case newspaper needs to be used the next day
那In case隔天報紙要用
But it's not used yet
不過都還沒用到
In theory, it was a very sweet year.
理論上呢 那一年非常特甜
That National Geographic
那個National Geographic
Just made a documentary about our story
就把我們這個故事拍了一個紀錄片
In the next year, 2001, every two years
在隔年了 2001 隔兩年
That is, two years ago we got another one
也就是兩年前我們又弄了一個
Another larger international experiment was organized
又組織了一個更大的國際實驗
This is cooperation with Taiwan's marine community
這是跟台灣的海洋界合作
we still fly
我們還是繼續飛
This cooperation was just mentioned to you
這個合作就是剛剛跟大家提的
we're going to explore the ocean
我們要去探測海洋
Both the atmosphere and the ocean
大氣跟海洋都要兼顧
So our domestic and foreign oceans
所以我們國內跟國外的海洋
Ships go to sea to detect
船隻都去海裡面去探測
It must have the detection instruments of this ocean
它要有這個海洋的探測儀器
Still have to go below 100 meters
還要去100公尺以下
The thermal structure of the ocean
海洋的熱力結構
Structure of Temperature Structure of Density
溫度的結構 密度的結構
See how it changes before and after the typhoon
看它隨著颱風經過前後的變化
To understand how much the ocean is affected by typhoons
來了解海洋受颱風多少影響
and how much it affects the subsequent development of the typhoon
以及它會影響颱風後來的發展有多大
The result you see is like this photo
這個結果各位看到像這張照片
we made a
我們就做了一個這樣的
very interesting surround
非常有趣的環繞
American planes fly in it
美國的飛機就在裡面飛行
We still need to use the phone in the air
我們在飛的空中裡面還要用電話
connect with computer
用電腦連線
in contact with each other
在互相聯繫
Because they don't want us to fly higher
因為他們不希望我們飛得比較高
about 13 kilometers
大概13公里
They fly at an altitude of only about 4 kilometers to 5 kilometers
他們飛在大概只有4公里到5公里的高空
They don't want us flying over their heads
他們不希望我們飛在他們頭頂
just drop things
就丟東西下來
Although the chances of hitting are very, very low
雖然打到的機會非常非常低
But they still hope not
不過他們還是希望不要
it's all planned
這都是有規劃的
This study is actually quite interesting
這個研究其實也蠻有趣的
So in 2004
所以在2004年
In fact we're only doing it for the second year
事實上我們才做的第二年
The news bureau made this an interesting topic
新聞局就把這個列為一個有趣的議題
as in
當成在
It is tantamount to promoting the development of Taiwan's technology
等於是宣導台灣的科技的發展的議題
this issue
這個議題
Coincidentally, I got one
剛好不巧的還得了一個
Introduced Award
引展的獎
It shouldn't have anything to do with the hero
這跟男主角應該沒有關係
The director is too strong
導演太強了
But more memorable
不過比較有紀念價值的是
Later, a documentary
後來也拍了一個紀錄片
This is the National Geographic Channel
這是 National Geographic Channel
he followed me
他就跟著我
The process of doing this task in 2008
去做這個任務的2008年的過程
I have a few copies of this documentary
這個紀錄片我有留了幾張
Our DVD if interested students today especially
我們的DVD如果今天特別是有興趣的同學
If you are interested or children
有興趣的話或是小朋友
I'm happy to share
我很樂意分享
Of course there are many rare photos in the air
在空中當然有很多很難得的照片
Everyone can see that if you are not in the sky, you can see a typhoon in your lower field of vision
各位可以看到你非在空中就看到一個颱風在你的下面視野之下
In fact, if mentioned at the beginning
事實上如果一開始提的
This is a beautiful scientific study
這是一個很美的科學的研究
But of course it has its challenges
可是當然它也有它的挑戰
because as a presenter
因為身為一個主持人
We have a great responsibility to make sure
我們有很大的責任要make sure
The whole process is safe
這整個過程是安全的
And of course we were able to do this research mainly because of government funding.
還有我們當然主要是因為政府的資助才能做這個研究
So be very careful
所以更非常借勝小心
Hope to achieve what we should do
希望有做到我們該做的成果
over the past ten years
過去十幾年來
Probably all the relevant research I have been engaged in is in this field.
大概我從事的相關研究都是在這個領域
Trying to answer questions about different aspects of the typhoon
在試著回答颱風各個不同層面的問題
Hope to find an updated answer
希望找到更新的答案
I was lucky enough to find some results
那也有很幸運的都找到一些結果
Well, of course I'm on this plane today.
那我今天當然是就這個飛機的
Introduced to you about the strategic measurement part
關策略性的量測部分跟大家介紹了
As I introduced at the beginning today
如同我今天一開始介紹
Typhoon measurement has many different aspects
颱風的量測有很多不同的面向
In fact, it is still under development
事實上還有在開發
and we're still working on it
而且我們還在努力之中
Maybe there will be more opportunities in the future
或許以後還有更多機會
Let me introduce more results
再跟大家介紹更多的成果
Of course it's a Vision
那當然這是一個Vision
That is to say, in fact there needs to be one more
就是說事實上需要有一個更多的
good scientists and researchers to participate
好的科學家跟研究人員來參與
In order to bring this research to a higher level
才能使這個研究進入更高的境界
And it can solve the problems of science and people's livelihood
而且可以解決科學跟民生的問題
Well I guess it's one of our visions
那我想這是我們的其中的一個Vision
then let me introduce to you
那我跟大家介紹
what chance is there in the future
未來還有什麼機會
In the United States, they have figured out a way to update
在美國呢他們已經想出更新的方法了
to replace the existing aircraft
要取代現有的飛機了
They use this very famous one called Global Hawk
他們用這個非常著名的這個叫做Global Hawk
Unmanned aircraft called Voice of the Sky
叫做天空之音的無人飛機
this plane is a reconnaissance plane
這個飛機是偵察機
was used in the Iraq war to detect
是在伊拉克戰爭被用來偵測
The so-called important key tool of where the enemy is
所謂的敵軍在哪的重要關鍵工具
The other plane is called the Predator
另外一架飛機叫 Predator
Just go fire the missiles, you probably know
就去發射飛彈 各位可能知道
This drone just happens to have a few
這個無人飛機剛好有幾架
Americans came up with an idea
美國人想出了一個idea
Donate to NASA Donate to NASA from the Department of Defense
捐給NASA 從國防部捐給NASA
NASA is going to use this plane to detect
美國的太空總署要用這個飛機來探測
First target to detect typhoon
第一個目標探測颱風
This experiment has been carried out
這個實驗已經進行了
currently flying
目前還在飛行
The plan for this experiment is well organized
這個實驗的計畫組織很好
just a good friend of mine
剛好是我一個好朋友
Here's a photo of him standing on this Global retreat
這是他站在這個Global後遣的照片
they will
他們將來
I've been experimenting with this aircraft since about last year
大概從去年開始已經在實驗用這個飛機
This Plane Flies Higher Unmanned Aircraft
這個飛機飛得更高無人飛機
Fly at an altitude of 18 kilometers
飛在18公里的高空
above the typhoon
在颱風的更上面
So he is less affected by the typhoon
所以他比較不受颱風影響
And he can fly for a long time at a time
而且他一次可以飛好久
There are a few days so you can constantly monitor the typhoon
有幾天所以可以不斷的monitor颱風
The organizer happened to be at the beginning of June
這個組織人剛好在6月初的時候
Almost two months ago, I visited Taiwan
快兩個月前有來拜訪台灣
Then I was also discussing with him whether they should consider
那我也跟他在討論他們將來是不是要把考慮
Fly this aircraft to the Pacific Northwest to try it out
把這個飛機試驗一下飛到西北太平洋來試看看
But we're now waiting for their results in the Atlantic
不過我們現在正在等候他們在大西洋的成果
if this goes well
如果這個進展順利的話
Maybe this will be the mainstream of typhoon observation around the world in the future
說不定這就是未來全世界觀測颱風的主流
Of course this plane is very expensive
那當然這個飛機非常的昂貴
Fortunately, the aircraft donated to them by the Ministry of National Defense of the country are doing such detection
還好他們是國家的國防部捐給他們的飛機在做這樣的探測
May change our future study of typhoons
可能會改變我們未來對颱風的研究
Instead of various observation tools
取代了各種的觀測的工具的
And this Gu Liang without any staff is safe Gu Liang
而且沒有任何人員的這個顧良安全的顧良
The last story is to tell you about the past 10 years
最後一個故事呢是跟大家講過去10年來
I travel all over the world like this
我就這樣走遍全世界
Every point is a place I've been
每一個點都是我去過的地方
So as a scientist
所以身為一個科學家
can be regarded as a person
也算是一個人
a variety of experiences
一個各種不同的體驗
We go to various places to meet and do experiments
我們到各個地方去開會去做實驗
to learn new things
去學習新的東西
Then I just talked about 2002
那我剛剛講了2002年呢
i was there once
我是到有一次
What about the typhoon seminar held by the World Meteorological Organization of the United Nations every four years?
每四年一次的聯合國的世界氣象組織的台風研討會呢
every Quadrennial
四年一次
2002 to CANES
2002到CANES
I just happened to experience my first dive in my life
我剛好順便體驗人生的第一個潛水活動
then the scientist
然後那科學家
this scientist is very famous
這位科學家非常有名
Just happened to go diving with me
剛好跟我一起潛到海底
just the two of us
就只有我們兩個
Just then we each had a baby
剛好那時候我們都各有一個Baby
So we hugged a CQCumbers sea cucumber each
所以我們就各抱了一個CQCumbers海參
It's like a baby passport
就好像Baby護照了一張
As a result, I now have a very good research understanding and cooperation with him.
結果我現在跟他有非常好的研究的默契跟合作
Maybe it's all because we once lived together under the sea
可能都是因為我們曾經在海底一起共生時過
The other one I just talked about
那另外一張我剛剛講了
We also went to Costoreca for the once-in-a-decade meeting of the World Meteorological Organization
我們也到Costoreca開這個世界氣象組織十年一次的會
I came to this place two years ago
兩年前呢還到這個地方
No one ever knows where to go
從來沒有人知道會想到要去的地方
Call Lara Union on Liu Niwang Island
叫Lara Union在劉尼旺島
in the indian ocean
在印度洋
south indian ocean
南印度洋
very nice beach
非常漂亮的海灘
Like this is not the same as Su this
就像這個跟不蘇這個
These so-called
在這邊的這一些所謂
This place in the prefecture of Mar
馬爾地府這個地方
world famous
世界知名的
then we just went to a meeting
那我們剛好去開會
I'm just talking and doing research
我只是要講說做研究
Actually there are many interesting parts
其實有很多有趣的部分
There are many people who are doing and are pursuing life
在做也有很多正在追尋人生的
direction of young friends
方向的年輕朋友
Maybe we can join this ranks in the future
或許以後也可以加入這個行列
I'm lucky enough to say
我比較幸運的就是說
I just happened to quote this Steve Jobs
我剛好引用這個 Steve Jobs
at Stanford University in 2005
在2005年在 Stanford 大學的
The content of this Speech
這個Speech 的內容
Although he is unfortunate
他雖然很不幸
he has passed away
他已經去世了
But he talked about it a few years ago
不過他幾年前談到說
life is about connecting this
人生就是要連接這個
a lot of bits and pieces
很多點點滴滴
I saw this DUTZ
我看到這個 DUTZ
It can be combined with my DUTZ DUTZ quite well
跟我的 DUTZ DUTZ 就蠻能結合的
Then I think I'm very lucky too
那我想我也是非常幸運的
Take what you have learned in the past
把過去所學的點點滴滴
shine up
燦起來
So right now at this
所以目前剛好在這個
very special
很特殊的
Research areas continue to evolve
研究領域繼續發展
Okay, what about yesterday? Today Vice President Peng mentioned
好 昨天呢 今天彭副院長提到了
We flew to the typhoon
我們就飛到台風去了
You can see we did a probe
各位可以看到我們做了一個探測
This information is placed on the website
這個資料都放在網頁上
This typhoon is still developing
這個台風還在發展之中
But I can't say much under the meteorological law.
可是根據氣象法我不能發表太多意見
But I think this typhoon may still be very threatening
不過我想這個台風可能還是很威脅很大
or please pay more attention
還是請大家要多留意
I was going to share a video
本來要分享一段影片
But let's put this short story of ours
不過我們把我們的這個簡短的故事
Also made a song and video
還做了一首歌跟影片
It was made by a college student of mine
是我一個大學的學妹做的
I made it into a MV
我把它做成一個MV
But this allows interested colleagues to perhaps go
不過這個就讓有興趣的同仁或許去
Find the answer of Fengshou and you will see
找一下豐收的答案就可以看到了
The last thing I want to tell you is
最後我要跟大家講的是
This study is actually very lucky
這個研究其實是非常幸運
It's because government funding gives us the opportunity to do
是因為政府的資助讓我們有機會做的
so i want to thank many people
所以我要感謝許多人
that's like thank god
那就好像謝天吧
Taiwanese kids are very smart
台灣的小孩非常的聰明
I heard that there is still this composition
聽說還有這一段作文照劇
of course it was a joke
那當然這是開玩笑的
yes
對啊
the last thing i want to say is
我最後要講的是
Thank you very much for the invitation of Academia Sinica
非常感謝中研院的邀請
Let everyone come together enthusiastically on the night of the typhoon
讓今天大家熱情的在台風夜一起來
Listen to me share our research abroad and experience
聽我分享我們的研究出國跟經驗
look forward to seeing you again
期待改天再會
thank you all
謝謝大家
Thank you Director Wu for your wonderful speech
謝謝吳主任的精采的演講
From very simple to cutting-edge research
從很通俗的到最尖端研究的東西
I'm the moderator and I usually control the time
我當主持人我通常是控制時間
So I hope it's 9 o'clock to let everyone go
所以我希望是9點就放大家走
12 minutes left now
現在剩下12分鐘
protection time
保護時間
quick to ask questions
要問問題的趕快
OK
OK
ok thank you for a very good presentation
好 謝謝你非常精采的演講
From what you just said, it seems
從你剛剛講的那個內容裡面看起來
The information of the ocean
海洋的那個資訊
very predictive
對預測非常
So maybe in the future the big breath will combine with the ocean
所以說不定以後大氣息會跟海洋會結合
i'm kidding
我這開玩笑
My question is actually
我問題其實是說
Unlike the surveillance in the air
不像那個空中的監測
You can fly through it quickly
你可以用飛機快速的穿越過
Then in the ocean when you have to do both sides
那在海洋你要做兩側的時候
Do you want to put a lot of ships?
難道要放很多艘船嗎
or is there anything massive
還是有什麼大規模
There can also be a monitoring method for sentient beings who go Z
又可以有Z走的眾生的監測方法
Thank you for this very good question
謝謝你這個非常好的問題
The first suggestion you just made
第一個你剛剛講的建議
It's actually very, very important
事實上是非常非常重要的
In fact, many atmospheres and oceans abroad
事實上在國外許多大氣跟海洋
is the same technology
是同一個科技一體的
Of course, there may be more appropriate and mature opportunities in China.
那當然在國內或許更適當成熟的機會
should develop in that direction
應該要往那個方向發展
What about observations at sea?
那海上的觀測呢
It's really difficult
的確比較困難
This is why ocean observations are not as rich as the atmosphere
這也是為什麼海洋觀測沒有大氣這麼豐富
the ocean
那這個汪洋大海
Each of your probes is actually very expensive
你每一個探測事實上是非常昂貴的
If you want to detect the phone before and after the typhoon
那如果要探測颱風前後的電話
it also has a lot of risk
它也有很大的風險
Because it can't get close don't say typhoon
因為它不能靠近不要說颱風
any let big to a degree
任何讓大到一個程度
can't get close anyway
反正不能靠近
So if their design is to go through this kind of research
所以他們的設計如果是要過這一種研究
At that time, the detection of the iTOP experiment just now
那時候剛剛那個iTOP實驗的探測
it requires making very rigorous forecasts of our atmosphere
它需要做非常嚴謹的我們大氣的預測
To create a typhoon, go there
製造颱風要往那邊走
Then it has to be 2 to 3 days before the typhoon goes in that direction
那它要在颱風往那個方向走的前2到3天
The ship is already going to that location to arrange various detection camps.
船就已經要到那個地點去佈置各種探測營氣
Then they will flash
然後他們就要閃
Then wait for the typhoon to pass
然後等颱風經過
So it's a little bit of a part like fishing
所以這是一個有一點部分是像釣魚一樣
Then if the typhoon doesn't go to those materials in the end
那如果颱風最後不去那些資料
still cold
還是涼了
But there is no way to cool enough to see the information
可是就是沒有辦法涼到想要看的資料
So currently is progress in this situation
所以目前是在這種情況進展
However, in these major international experiments
不過在這幾個國際的大實驗
It usually arranges more points just to ask for safety
它通常就是為了要求安全它就佈置好多點
A web of data connected in one line
連成一條線的一個資料網
Let the typhoon cool down to the surrounding area no matter where the typhoon passes
讓颱風不管從哪裡經過都會涼到颱風周邊的資料
Especially what happened to the seabed before the typhoon passed by
特別是颱風經過前海底怎麼樣
What does the bottom of the sea look like when you pass by
經過時跟後海底變成什麼樣子
If it's all cold enough, there will be results.
那都涼到的話就可以有結果
that result
那這個結果
This food test was completed almost two years ago.
這糧測在快兩年前才完成的
At present, many scientists are paying attention to this research work
目前正許多科學家正在重視這個研究工作
so very avant-garde
所以是非常的前衛
And there should be many new results to introduce in the future
而且將來應該會有很多新的成果可以介紹
I did not talk about the results of this part of the results today
我今天沒有談成果的這個部分的成果
If a large area grain survey is to be done
如果要做一個大面積的糧測
possible over the ocean
在海洋上面有可能進行
Yes, the ocean now has some automatic instruments too
對 海洋現在也有一些自動的儀器
But what is the purpose of its grain testing?
可是它做的糧測的目的呢
I might say for example
我舉例可能說
I have some now with a grain measuring instrument called the Argo
我現在有一些有一個糧測儀器叫做Argo
This instrument is very interesting
這個儀器非常有趣
The world has now deployed thousands of different seas around the world
全世界現在已經佈置了數千個在全世界不同的海上
But its disadvantage is that it has no faults
可是它的缺點是它沒有毛病
so it floats
所以它會飄
so you don't ignore where it is
所以你沒有空視它在哪
finally
最後呢
over a period of time
經過一段時間之內
All will float to the shore
所有的都會飄到岸邊去
There is no way to stay where you want at sea
都沒辦法留在海上要的地方
I have no choice but to let it go
這沒辦法就只好再放
what about it
那它呢
it will be because of the sunshine every day
它會因為每天日照
it will have some density change
它會有一些密度的改變
it will sink into the sea
它就會沉到海裡面去
then measure
那就量了
Then time, a certain time, it floats up again
然後時間 一定時間它又浮上來
When it floated up, it measured the entire vertical data again.
浮上來的時候就又量了整個垂直的一個資料
then when it floats up
然後它浮上來的時候
Its antenna can receive satellite signals
它的天線就可以接收到衛星的訊號
It can transmit data to the satellite
它就可以傳資料到衛星
There is such a measure to pass the data out
把資料傳出來 是有這樣的量測
So different scientists are indeed designing
所以不同的科學家的確在設計
Different measuring instruments help us solve
不同的量測儀器幫我們解決
This is not a problem that ships can solve
這個不是船可以解決的問題
it can use a ship to deploy this instrument
它可以用船去布置這種儀器
then let it walk on the sea
然後就讓它在海上散步
Then you can measure a lot
然後就可以量到很多
There are ups and downs to measure the data
還有上下起伏就可以量到資料
The more active approach in our experiment is
那比較積極的做法在我們那個實驗裡面是
fly by plane
用飛機 飛
Because the ship is sometimes slow, there is a risk
因為船有時候比較慢 有風險
Fly near the typhoon by plane
用飛機飛到颱風的附近
From the plane, the plane has to fly lower
從飛機 那飛機要飛得比較低空
Probably can only fly at an altitude of 1000 meters or 300 meters
大概只能飛在1000公尺或是300公尺的高空
Under those conditions, drop the instrument
在那樣的條件之下 把儀器投下去
After that instrument was thrown into the sea,
那那個儀器投到海裡面之後
The ocean's instruments will dive down to detect
海洋的儀器就會潛下去探測
What about a few days later?
那幾天後呢
It will be recycled than
那比起還會回收
because it is very expensive compared to
因為比起非常昂貴
Then it can also be detected
那這樣也可以探測
But this whole design
可是這個整個設計
Requires a lot of technology including engineering
需要非常多的包括工程的技術
But everyone is developing
可是都有人在發展
especially in
特別是在
Some advanced countries like the United States have
先進的一些像美國這些國家有
It's good that this kind of facility is doing this kind of research work
很好的這種設施在做這種研究工作
Then our domestic marine community also has related issues.
那我們國內的海洋界也有相關的
nice
不錯的
some research like this
這樣的一些研究的
some experience
的一些經驗
So I did this international cooperation just now
所以做了這個剛剛的國際合作
good
好
That is
那就是
good last man
好最後一人
use that microphone
用那個麥克風
ok
ok
that's in
那個在
Forecasting the Taiwan in the Taiwan area
預測臺灣地區的那個臺灣
It seems that Taiwan is doing
好像臺灣有在做
Japan is also doing
日本也有在做
America is doing
美國有在做
The information on the seven items seems to be
那那個七項的資料好像
Countries are exchanging
各國都有在交換
But often that predicts
但是常常那個預測出來
like
好像
Every country will be different
每個國家會有一些不一樣
where is the reason
那這個原因是在哪裡
that Taiwan
那臺灣
In the forecast near Taiwan
在預測臺灣附近的
Taiwan's path when
臺灣的路徑的時候
Does Taiwan have any advantages?
臺灣有沒有什麼樣的優勢
The second one is that it seems that in the past few years
那第二個就是說好像過去幾年來
The Taiwan that passed the seventh place in Taiwan seems to be smaller than the average number
那個臺灣經過臺灣第七的那個臺灣好像比平均數字小
Then it seems that the chance to hear the strong Taiwan seems to be relatively small
然後好像聽到那個強烈臺灣的那個機會好像也比較少
what is the reason
那個原因是怎麼樣
Nanakka may be due to loading
那那克卡可能是因為負荷的原因
But I feel that the number will be relatively small
但是感覺到那個數量會比較少
It seems to be different from the statistic of a writer you mentioned just now
好像跟那個剛才您提到一個寫者的統計好像不太一樣
don't know how
不曉得是怎麼樣
Okay, let me answer the second question first
好我先從後面第二個問題回答
In fact, just now you mentioned whether it was some typhoon activity
事實上剛剛你提到說是不是一些颱風的活動
The frequency or intensity or character of passing through Taiwan
經過臺灣的頻率或者是強度或特徵
Have there been any statistically significant changes over the past few years
在過去幾年是否有一些統計性比較有意義的變化
In fact, the typhoon has a certain variation in nature.
這個事實上颱風本來在大自然就它一定的變異
Then there's some variability from year to year
那在年以年之間就有一些變異性
So if you look at the very short angle
所以如果你用很短的角度來看
The significance of this statistic is not necessarily very special.
這個統計的意義不見得是非常有特別的意義
In other words, we don't really know yet
換句話說我們目前其實不太知道
Is there such a noticeable change
是否有這樣明顯的變化
That some need you to strengthen some of these points
那有些需要您強的一些這些點
More precise statistics may be needed
可能需要更精確的統計數字
we just know
我們才知道
But it is clear that scientists
不過比較明確的是科學家
actually really understand
其實是的確很了解
For example, we are in the tropical ocean
譬如說我們在熱帶的海洋
There will be a so-called holy cause
會有所謂聖因的現象
sea ​​temperature will change
海溫會有變化
While these changes happen every few years
當這些每隔幾年變化發生的時候
Typhoon Occurrence Area
颱風的發生區域
with some of its activities indeed
跟它的一些活動的確
will change
就會改變
We already know more about these
那這些我們已經有比較多了解了
That's for a place close to Taiwan
那針對靠近台灣的這個地步
partial change
部分的改變
In fact our statistics
事實上我們的統計數字
relatively without an obvious age
比較沒有一個明顯的年紀的
or change over the years
或多年間的變化
We are less clear about this
這個我們比較不明確
The other one needs more research
那另外那個需要更多的研究
So back to the question you asked at the beginning
那回到您剛剛一開始提的這個問題
What are the forecasts for each country?
各國的預測呢
Meteorological data from all over the world
的確全世界的氣象資料
under the framework of WMO
在WMO的架構之下
on the World Meteorological Organization
就世界氣象組織
is fully opened
是完全opened
So people all over the world can make predictions
所以全世界人都可以做預測
The so-called official meteorological units of each country
每一個國家的所謂的官方的氣象單位
But each country has its own computer model
可是每個國家有自己的電腦模式
So it doesn't predict exactly the same
所以它的預測結果不完全會一樣
This is because of the design of the schema
這是因為模式的設計
How to enter the computer mode with its data
跟它資料怎麼進入電腦模式的方法
different answers will be different
不同答案就會有所不同
Then sometimes everyone's results are the same
那有時候大家的結果很一致
when this happens
當這種情況發生的時候
This typhoon is likely to be well controlled
這個颱風很可能就很好掌控
But when everyone is quite different
可是當大家都差異性比較大的時候
It highlights that the typhoon has relatively high uncertainty.
就凸顯那個颱風有比較高的不確定性
At the end of the day, every country has to make human judgments
那每個國家最後要做人為的判斷的時候
The result may vary
的結果就有可能會出入
So what special so-called advantage does Taiwan have?
那我們台灣有什麼特別的所謂的advantage
or advantage
或是優勢呢
Basically, when the typhoon is very close to Taiwan
基本上呢當颱風非常靠近台灣的時候
Usually the location of the typhoon we do in Taiwan
通常我們台灣所做的颱風的位置
and analysis of its nearby movement
以及它的附近的移動的分析
will be more accurate than other countries
會比其他國家來得更精確
because it affects
因為它在影響
So our input will compare
所以我們的投入會比較
Compared with the so-called extra manpower
比較所謂的特別多人力
For example, he is also concerned about Japan
那譬如說日本他也在關心
But because he is not comfortable in his country
可是因為不自在他的國土
He's just following normal procedures
他就是按照一般的正常程序處理
so there are some
所以有一些
Then there are some very detailed information about our local radar in Taiwan, etc.
那還有一些我們台灣局部的雷達等等的那個很細節的資料
Our weather analysts may use a higher amount
我們的氣象研判人員可能用的量就會比較高
Then in other countries because they don't have the first line to see these materials
那在其他國家因為他們沒有第一線看到這些資料
they may not be useful
他們可能就沒有用
will be slightly different
就會略有差別
So statistically speaking
那所以統計上來講
Currently there are different
目前整個西北太平洋各個不同的
From the United States, Japan, Hong Kong, Beijing
從美國日本香港北京
South Korea wait until our Central Weather Bureau
韓國等等到我們中央氣象局
The overall average level of the forecast of this typhoon
的這個颱風的預測的總平均的水準
Basically, if we talk about predicting the final level in Taiwan, it is probably the same order
台灣基本上如果談預測最後的水準是大概都是同一個 order
about the same
差不多上下的
nothing special
沒有特別的
That is to say, everyone is the same
就是說大家都一樣的
level
水準
At present, this level is about
那這個水準目前大概
Average error of forecast for one day
一天的預測的平均誤差
perhaps
大概
average about nine
平均大概九
10 to 100 kilometers
10到100公里
so
所以
This may not be a big problem for other countries like the United States
這對別的國家像美國可能不是大問題
because big
因為大
It is not a small issue for Taiwan
對台灣問題就很不小了
because
因為呢
We predict to go to Hualien
我們預測要到花蓮
Maybe in Taitung, but also in Yilan or Taikeelung
可能在台東也可以在宜蘭或台基隆
In addition, our vacation is based on counties and cities
再加上我們的放假是以縣市為單位的
that's finer
那更細了
are within the margin of error of this forecast.
都在這個預報的誤差範圍
this is our difficulty
這是我們的困難之處
So I leave that question to
所以我把剛剛那個問題留給
those two
那兩位
two seniors
兩位的前輩
good
好
that last question
那最後一個問題
No
沒有的
is there a last question
有沒有在最後一個問題
good
好
Thanks
謝謝
Professor Wu's very brilliant speech
吳教授非常精采的演講
I've always been curious
其實我一直很好奇
because we are in Taiwan
因為我們在台灣
Exposure to typhoons since childhood
從小就接觸颱風
The typhoon that I heard from childhood
那從小聽到的颱風
That's what Professor Wu said at the beginning
也是那個吳教授一開始就講的
It is the disaster brought by typhoon
就是台颱風帶來的災害
then i always
那我一直都
I am very curious, since the power of disasters brought by typhoons is so great
非常好奇 既然颱風帶來的災害威力都這麼大
Then believe that he also has such great energy
然後相信他也有這麼大的能量
Is there any way to convert the energy of this typhoon into kinetic energy beneficial to human beings?
那有沒有辦法把這種颱風的能量轉變成對人類有益的動能
Thanks
謝謝
Thank you for this simple
謝謝你 這個簡單來講
Let's talk about wind energy first
我們先講風能好了
Yes indeed we have some so-called WinMill on the western or northern coast of Taiwan
是的確我們在台灣西部或北部沿海有一些所謂的WinMill
When this rotates, electricity is generated
這個轉動的時候會產生電能
But the current design of these things
可是目前的這些東西的設計
Basically, the wind speed must be below a certain wind speed.
它基本上大概風速都要在一定的風速以下
In fact, above a certain wind speed
事實上超過一定的風速
basically dangerous to the operation of its machinery
基本上對它的機具的運作就有危險
it may break etc
它可能會斷裂等等
it just won't work
它就不能運作
Therefore, the strong wind of the typhoon will completely shut down the device under that condition.
所以颱風的強風在那種條件都完全是要關機的
so useless
所以用不到
Then this may be limited by our modern technology for this typhoon.
那這可能是受限於我們現代的科技對於這個颱風的這種
With such a strong wind speed
那麼強烈的風速的情況之下
We don't have a way to use that energy yet
我們還沒有方法把那個能量把它用出來
it's really a pity
的確是非常可惜
But I haven't heard of it yet
可是目前我也還沒有聽說
Is there any way to convert this part out
這個部分有沒有什麼方法可以把它轉換出來
Then we can also imagine that in fact
那我們也可以想像事實上
For example, the normal storage of water in the reservoir can help generate electricity
譬如說水庫平常蓄水可以協助發電
But in fact when the typhoon comes
可是事實上當颱風來的時候
sometimes it's time to drain
有時候是要趕快排水
so there is no way
所以根本也沒辦法
do these many operations
做這些很多的操作
So this type belongs to the very violent, violent, and temporary type.
所以這一種屬於很猛烈的、劇烈的、臨時性的這一種
how to use it
東西的確要怎麼用它
Personally, I still need a lot
我個人來看是還需要很大的
There is still a lot of room for improvement to get to that city
就是還有很大的進步的空間才能到那個城市
Some energy that can transform it from negative to positive and so on
可以把它從負面轉化為正面的一些能量等等
That
那
At present, some scientists think of a stream like black grass
目前有一些科學家想到的是說像黑草這麼一股
such a strong current
這麼強的海流
Can it also be partially converted into electricity?
是不是也可以部分轉化成電能
but these are watching
不過這些都在看
stage of planning
規劃的階段
So these issues are indeed technological challenges
所以這些議題的確是科技的挑戰
I can only say this now
只能現在只能這樣講
ok that time is up
好 那時間到了
We are very grateful to Director Wu for his wonderful speech
我們這個非常謝謝吳主任的精彩的演講
I will also take him to invite you to visit him at National Taiwan University another day
我也帶他邀請你們改天去台大找他玩
The Department of Meteorology of National Taiwan University came out of that Gongguan MRT station.
他們台大氣象系就在那個公館捷運站出來
About 100 meters away
大概100公尺左右的地方
There, the vicinity of Lu Mingtang is very beautiful
那裡 陸明堂的附近非常漂亮
You can play with him
你們可以去找他玩
Okay, we thank Director Wu
好 我們謝謝吳主任